Academia Sinica's February Governor's Salary Banquet Lecture Begins
中央研究院2月份知事饷宴演讲会开始
We ask Vice President Huang Bansheng to host for us
我们请黄半生副院长为我们主持
thank you all distinguished guests good night everyone
谢谢各位贵宾大家晚安
Good night
晚安
Today was supposed to be hosted by Vice President Chen Jianren
今天本来应该是陈建仁副院长来主持
But because he's going abroad, I'm the agent
但是因为他出国所以由我来代理
Then next week it seems to be me too
那么下个礼拜好像也是由我
Next week's Humanities
下个礼拜的是人文的
so i'm going to read the speech
所以我要念一下講稿
Because I'm the Associate Dean for Humanities
因為我是人文的副院長
so relatively unfamiliar
所以比較陌生
Feel sorry
抱歉
Welcome to today's feast of knowledge
非常歡迎各位來參加今天的知識饗宴
Everyone knows that the Feast of Knowledge is
大家知道知識饗宴是
Academia Sinica is a very important activity to promote popular science education
中研院推廣科普教育很重要的活動
have been around for a long time
行之有年
Every month we invite experts and scholars from various fields inside and outside the school
每個月我們都邀請院內外各個領域的專家學者
Come here to talk about the latest academic research and scientific development
來這裡跟大家談最新的學術研究跟科學發展
It is our pleasure to invite you to our hospital to divide and administer biology tonight
今天晚上我們很高興請到本院分治生物
Research Fellow
研究所的特評研究員
Ms. Bien
儀師美燕氏
Let's talk about world food security and crisis
來跟大家談世界糧食安全以危機
where to go
何從何去
Well, everyone saw that the self-introduction of the academician mentioned
那麼各位看到院士的這個自我介紹裡面提到
Because he saw his inner and outer grandfathers as eggs since he was a child
他因為從小看到內外祖父都是物卵
See this farmer and nature Hakata
看到這個農夫跟大自然博多
So he chose his
所以他選擇了他的這個
subject of this study
這個研究的主題
is rice
就是稻米
Then he started from the university and research institute
那麼他從在大學跟研究所
I studied at the Department of Occupational Diseases of Central University
所讀的是中心大學職病系
Department of Occupational Pathology
就是職務病理系
Then go to the United States to apply for a license
然後到美國申照
After receiving a Ph.D. in pathology from the University of Arkansas
得到阿肯所大學的職務病理學博士之後
Postdoctoral research in the United States
在美國擔任博士後研究
The hospital came back to our hospital in 1989
醫院是在1989年回國到本院
Institute of Molecular Biology Continuing Research
分子生物學研究所繼續研究
Choose the most local
選擇了最具本土性
and is the most important food crop in the world
而且是全球最重要的糧食作物
Rice as research material
水稻作為研究材料
So far, many breakthrough studies have found that
至今已經有很多突破性的研究發現
For example, the discovery of a gene that controls flood tolerance in rice
譬如說發現控制水稻耐淹水的基因
Level Molecular Mechanism
級分子機制
Unraveling only rice seeds among all stocks for decades
解開數十年來所有股類中只有水稻種子
The secret to germination and growth in water
可以在水中發芽跟生長的秘密
The results were published in important international journals
這個成果發表在國際很重要的期刊
Hospital doctors are also invited to speak at international conferences
醫院士也理理受邀在國際大行會議
Speech to domestic and foreign organizations
跟國內外機構演講
And won many domestic and foreign awards
並獲得許多國內外的大獎
Elected as a Fellow of the Academy of Sciences for the Developing World in 2005
2005年當選為發展中世界科學院的院士
Elected to the American Association for the Advancement of Science in 2005
2005年當選美國科學促進學會
In 2012, that is, last year, he was elected as an academician of the Chinese Academy of Sciences
更在2012年也就是去年當選中研院院士
Since 1993, the academician successfully completed the world's first rice gene transfer using agrobacterium
院士從1993年成功完成全球第一個利用農感菌轉職水稻基因
He continues to use genetic engineering technology to improve rice varieties
他持續利用基因工程技術改良水稻品種
Developed many innovative biotechnologies
發展許多創新生物科技
He also led the teams of Chung Hsing University and Asia University in the Institute of Agriculture, Academia Sinica
他更領導中研院農事所中興大學跟亞洲大學的團隊
From 2003 to 2012, a huge rice map was completed
從2003到2012完成一個龐大的水稻圖種
Mutant stock and gene database
突變種原庫及基因資料庫
Discovered the functions of many important genes
發現許多重要基因的功能
Recently, BioGate, a foundation funded by BioGate, has received funding
最近更得到BioGate就是BioGate資的基金會的經費
Study how to increase rice photosynthesis efficiency to yield
研究如何增加水稻光合作用效率以產量
Significantly enhance the international life of rice research in Taiwan
顯數提升台灣水稻研究在國際間的生活
Then in another introduction
那麼在另外一張介紹裡面
He also mentioned that the population has been increasing because
他也提到人口因為一直在增加
However, there is obviously no significant increase in food
可是糧食顯然沒有很顯著的增加
Such a game is actually a very
這樣一個賽局其實是一個非常
a challenging question
具有挑戰性的一個問題
last year
去年
ah
啊
group just
團體剛
The Secretary-General of the Chinese Academy of Sciences came to the Hospital of Traditional Chinese Medicine
中作科學院的秘書長來中醫院
because that day
因為當天
When all the officers don't know where to go
所有長官都不知道去哪裡的時候
I had to meet him
只好由我來接見他
he raised a question
他就提到了一個問題
he just said
他就說
Pope is against genetic modification
教皇是反對基因改造
this
這個
ah
啊
rice
水稻的
he obviously
他顯然
Is my report right?
我的報導對不對
if i am wrong i will
我如果錯了我就
I'll be better anyway
反正我就會更正好
this love
這個情
He said but the pope is the pope who just abdicated
他說可是教皇就是剛退位的教皇
against genetic modification
是反對基因改造
He said that because the Pope in his youth
他說因為教皇在年輕時代
study in germany
在德國念書
Influenced by Heidegger's philosophy
深受海德格的哲學的影響
Then Heidegger is of course the second century
那麼海德格當然是二世紀
very important philosophy
非常重要的哲學
one of the most important philosophers
最重要的哲學家之一
He opposes excessive intervention and destruction
他反對過度的干預跟破壞大致
but he said
可是他說
He thinks he sees things differently than the Pope
他認為他的看法跟教皇不同
pope your people your believers
教皇你的子民你的信徒
What a sorrow
多是哀樂啊
How can you not modify his genes
你怎麼能不改造他的基因
have more of this
有更多的這個
So I guess I'm hosting today's talk
那我想我因為要主持今天這個演講
Reminds me of this conversation last year
想起這個去年這個對話
Then I think today's topic is very meaningful
那我覺得今天這個主題非常有意義
It is world food security and crisis
就是世界糧食的安全跟危機
not where to go but where to go
不是何去何從而是何從何去
we applaud
我們掌聲歡迎
Yu Xiuyan
余秀妍
good
好
Vice President Wang thank you for the introduction
王副院長謝謝王副院長介紹
and good night everyone
然後各位來賓大家晚安
Good night
晚安
Thank you so much for a hard day
非常謝謝你們經過一天的辛苦
Then I have to come here for class in the evening
然後晚上還要來這邊上課
I wish to say this is not a serious class
我希望說這個不是一個嚴肅的課
because what we are going to talk about today
因為我們今天要講的主題呢
Is it related to our current life and future life
是跟我們目前的生活還有未來的生活
are closely related
是息息相關的
is a very important topic
是非常重要的一個題目
we should all know
我們都應該了解
I hope that you will finally feel that
那希望說你們會最後會覺得說
don't need this trip
不須此行
I'll wait
那我等下
This is because I watched this speech
這個因為我看這個演講
Queued for two hours is a bit long
排了兩個鐘頭有點長
Then I hope that it can be done within an hour and a half
那我希望說能夠盡量在一個半鐘頭
end it within
之內把它結束
and leave some time for people to ask this question
然後留一些時間讓大家來問這個問題
because it's a matter of great concern
因為這是很受關心的問題
I often go out to lecture in class
我常常出去上課演講
really everyone cares
真的大家都很關心
Then I feel that there are many places I don’t understand
然後都覺得很多地方不了解
Then we need to make some clarifications
然後我們需要來做一些說明
The media is also very concerned about this issue.
那媒體也是非常的關心這個議題
You can always watch
大家也可以常常看
The media often come to visit me
在媒體上面常常都會來訪問我
discuss these issues
討論這些問題
So I think the media, the people
所以我覺得媒體、人民
In fact, they are very concerned about this issue
其實都非常關心這個問題
I feel like it's just the government that doesn't really care
我覺得好像只有政府不怎麼關心
So I hope there is still a chance
所以希望說還是能夠有機會
enable them to understand the seriousness of the problem
能夠讓他們能夠了解這個問題的嚴重性
So let's start now with what I'm going to talk about
那我們就現在來開始講我要講的內容
So in this twentieth century
所以在這個二十世紀
In the past 100 years, our technology has advanced very fast
在一百年來我們的科技進步非常的快
From burning this without a light to being able to use a computer now
從燒這個沒有燈到現在能夠用電腦
Do various searches with Google
用Google做各種的search
Then from this ship to space, it is said that it can fly to the sky
然後從這個輪船到太空說能夠飛到天空
technology advances very fast
技術進步非常快
But at the same time, in this one hundred years
可是同時在這一個一百年的之間
Our population has also nearly quadrupled
我們的人口也增加了快要四倍
The rate of increase of this population
這個人口的增加的速度
This one was written from 1750
這個是從1750年開始寫
you see 1500 years
你看到1500年
15 about 607 years later
15大概607年之後
From the beginning, the speed of increase is very fast
開始就增加的速度就非常的快
wait a minute we'll mention there was a green revolution
等一下我們會提到有一個綠色革命
was started in 1960
是在1960年開始
until almost the end of 2000
到差不多2000年結束
around this time
差不多這個時候
during the first green revolution
第一次綠色革命的時候
The population is growing at its fastest rate
人口是增加速度最快的一個時候
Now our population increase is not over
現在我們的人口的增加沒有結束
did not stop
沒有停下來
actual birth rate
實際上人口的出生率
It's actually going down
其實是在下降的
But because of these populations
可是因為這些的人口
In the next 30, 40 years
在未來的 30 、40 年
he will start
他會開始
No 20, 30 years
不 20、30 年
will begin to have many children
會開始生很多的小孩子
so this is a
所以這是一個
It will continue to be the cause of our population pressure
它會繼續造成我們人口壓力的原因
the distribution of the population
那在人口的分布
From Africa Latin America Asia Oceania
從非洲 拉丁美洲 亞洲 大洋洲
North America Europe or Worldwide
北美洲 歐洲 或是全球
You can see that Africa is indeed the most populous
你可以看到非洲的確是人口最多
latin america asia
拉丁美洲 亞洲
But what about the rate of population increase?
可是呢 人口的增加的速率
this different color
這個不同的顏色
are saying
都是在表示說
it's at a different time
它在不同的時間呢
Indeed, it has been decreasing
的確是一直有在降低
so far
到現在目前為止
rate of population increase
人口增加的速度
In fact, there is no rate of death
其實沒有比死亡的速率
how high is it
來的高多少
One is 2.5% One is 2.2%
一個是 2.5% 一個是 2.2%
so we all know
所以我們大家都知道
population cannot increase
人口不能再增加
can't be that fast
速率不能那麼快
But the problem is that so many people exist
可是問題是現存了那麼多人就存在
it is going to have a baby
它要生小孩
Then how do we feed so many people
那我們怎麼樣子來餵這麼多人
At the same time, a very important issue related to food is energy.
那我們同時跟這個糧食有關的一個很重要一題是能源
The proportion of this energy
這個能源所佔的比例
Oil 37%
石油三七%
Coal 25%
煤炭25%
Then Natural Gas 23%
然後天然氣23%
Other very small proportions are some other energy sources
其他的很小的比例才是一些其他能源
What about nuclear power?
那核能呢
Press 6% again
再按6%
That's biomass
那這個是生物質
reproductive energy
生殖能源
And then hydrogen or solar wind and so on
然後氫氣或是太陽能風力等等
Its proportion is actually very low
它佔的比例其實是非常的低的
Of course, what else is hot?
那當然其他還有什麼地熱啦
there are others this and others
還有另外其他的這個還有其他
it's sun hot
這是太陽熱
that's solar and so on
那這是太陽能等等
So our share of renewable energy
所以我們的再生能源所佔的比例
So far there is no way to improve
到現在為止還沒有辦法提高
because it costs too much
是因為它的成本實在是太高了
The current energy
那現在目前有的這些能源
relatively low price
價格又相對很低
So everyone is interested in the development of this renewable energy
所以大家都對發展這個再生能源
not so positive
就沒有那麼積極
That's just a few days ago
那這個在才前幾天而已
What about our gasoline?
這個我們的汽油呢
This gas once in Taiwan
這個在台灣的汽油一次
rose to an all-time high
升到歷史新高
Although it has dropped a little these days
雖然說這幾天有稍微降一點
But I believe this number will still be a normal
可是相信這一號還是會有一個常態
In this way, the energy is actually reduced.
那這樣子能源其實是在減少的
Many of the things we mentioned just now
剛剛我們提到的很多的
various energy sources that currently exist
各種的目前存在的能源
Able to use in addition to coal
能夠使用除了煤炭
It can be used for more than two hundred years
大概可以用兩百多年之外
Most of the others are around fifty years old
其他的大部分都在五十年上下
gasoline or natural gas
汽油或是天然氣
natural gas course most recent usa
天然氣當然最近美國
it has found some
它是有發現了一些
oily natural gas
油液炎的天然氣
so yes things are changing a bit
所以是情況是有點改變
There are other sources of energy like remineralization
還有其他的能源像又礦
about fifty years
也差不多是五十年左右
So everyone is speculating on nuclear energy
所以核能大家在炒
About fifty years
大概只炒五十年
Because it's useless in the future
因為以後也是沒有用
So the energy goes down like this
所以能源是這樣下降
This is how the population rises
人口是這樣上升的
But the speed at which our food is produced
可是我們糧食的生產的速度
actually slow down
其實是慢下來的
Such a gap between population and food
這樣子人口跟糧食這個缺口
Let's see now that this is 2010
我們現在你看這是2010年
We are still at the beginning
我們現在還在這個開頭而已
Nearly 40 years to come
未來還有將近40年的時間
such a long time
這麼長一個時間
How do we fill this big gap
我們怎麼樣子來補這個大缺口
it's a big challenge
這是一個很大的挑戰
so many people
人口那麼多
every mouth
每一張口
Every mouth has something to eat
每一個嘴巴都要吃東西
How can we produce enough of this food
我們如何能夠生產這個足夠的糧食
to feed so many people
來餵這麼多人
This is where we study plants
這是我們做研究植物的
research in agriculture
研究農業的
study of rice
研究稻米的
We often think about this question
我們常常都在想這個問題
But I think people who do medicine
不過我覺得做醫學的人
probably don't think about it
大概不太會想這個問題
people in medicine want to say
醫學的人都希望說
people are still healthy
人還是健康一點
grow thinner
長瘦一點
But I was at the United Daily News 10 years ago
可是我在10年前在聯合報呢
I wrote an article at that time
那時候就寫了一篇文章
It is said that a healthy and long-lived human being may not have enough to eat in a decade or two
說一二十年後健康長壽的人類可能吃不飽
So it's been 10 years
所以已經10年過去了
I was talking about ten or twenty years
我那時候是說一二十年
But now it's been 10 years
可是現在已經10年過去了
In fact, the problem is getting worse
實際上這個問題是越來越嚴重
That doesn't seem to have attracted too much attention.
那好像也還沒有引起太多的重視
let's start now
那我們現在先一開始
Let me tell you first
先跟大家講一下先了解說
Where is the serious form of the problem to be addressed today
今天要講的問題的嚴重形式在哪裡
But first let me give you some background
可是我先介紹給大家一些背景
That is, how does our food come from?
就是說我們的糧食是怎麼來的
Then our human culture actually followed agriculture
那我們的人類文化其實是跟著農業走的
3.8 billion years ago
在三十八億年前
Life begins on our planet
我們地球上面開始有生命
and then successively
然後後來陸陸續續
Then some various creatures came out.
就有一些各種各樣的生物就出來了
what about this flower
那這個花呢
Where's the first flower and insect?
第一個花和昆蟲呢
Appeared about 130,000,000 years ago
大概是在一億三千年前才開始出現
Homo sapiens really have such a developed mind
而智人真的是比較有這個發達的頭腦的
What about this award?
這個這個領獎內呢
appeared between 400,000 and 250,000 years ago
在四十到二十五萬年前才出現
So in the history of this earth
所以在這個地球的歷史上面
came very late
是非常晚才出現的
But it is the smartest animal
可是它是最聰明的動物
but also the most destructive animal
可是也是最具有破壞性的動物
what about our ancestors
那我們的祖先呢
when it first started
剛開始的時候呢
he hunts
他是靠打獵的
He runs wherever there are animals
哪裡有動物他就往哪裡跑
That's why it migrates everywhere
那這個所以到處遷徙
So from Africa 130,000 years ago
所以從非洲在十三萬年前
Start migrating to Europe
開始遷徙往歐洲啊
Then this Asia
然後這個亞洲啊
Then to America
然後又到美洲這樣子
such a migration
這樣子的遷徙
That's what our ancestors said
那可是呢我們的祖先說
Wow, it's really tiring to fight all over the place.
哇 這個到處打烈實在是覺得很累
But no one owns a grocery store
可是呢 沒有人開雜貨店
how do we settle down
我們怎麼定居下來
Do we still want to keep pulling like this?
我們還要這樣子一直一直不斷的牽起嗎
so what
那所以呢
They found out one day that there seemed to be some food somewhere
他們有一天發現 好像某些地方有一些食物
can we stop there
可以讓我們停下來 在那裡
can be used as food
可以當糧食
So in the beginning, they won't keep walking
所以開始呢 他們就不會再不斷的一直走
At the beginning, it was a little bit closer to the area of ​​grain production.
開始有一點在比較接近這個糧食的生產的地區呢
start walking around there
開始就在那附近走動
And in the end, I found this grain
那最後呢 發現這個糧食呢
We can also plant it to reproduce it
我們也可以種它來繁殖它
So when more and more food is planted
所以糧食越種越多的時候
it settles down
它就定居下來了
So the ancestors settled down
所以呢 祖先定居下來
So now there are still many chairs in the world
所以現在全世界上還有很多的椅子
That is, we can see that this was developed by human beings.
就是可以看到說人類開發的這個
Gikyo
宜京
In addition to planting this
那除了種這個
Of course humans are just speaking from Africa
當然人類是從非洲剛剛講的
means from africa
是說從非洲開始
to various countries
到各個國家
After that, everyone started to grow this crop
那後來大家就開始種這個作物之後
He also started to improve
他也開始改良
Then many places are doing this at the same time
那同時很多地方都在做這件事情
So 10,000 years ago
所以在一萬年前呢
In this America they have corn
在這個美洲他們有玉米啊
pumpkins, beans, etc.
南瓜這個豆子這一類的
Thirteen thousand years ago in Europe there were
一萬三千年前在歐洲有
wheat barley beans
小麥大麥豆類的
that big
那大
What about China nine thousand years ago
中國呢在九千年前
started with soybeans and so on
就開始有大豆等等
So what about this culture?
所以其實這個文化呢
is in many places
是在很多的地方
while developing
同時在發展的
Then our ancestors were very powerful
那我們的祖先是很厲害
from them to us
從他們開始我們一直到
this latest this
這個最近的這個
Where's the breeder?
育種學家呢
Breeding techniques that can be exploited
可以利用育種的技術
This crop can be improved
可以改進這個作物
So for thousands of years
所以數千年來呢
Humans have used breeding
人類已經利用育種
to engineer the genes of countless crops
來改造無數作物的基因
this is raw corn
這個是原始的玉米
it encourages very little
它的鼓勵非常的少
the shell is very hard
殼非常的硬
you can hardly bite
你幾乎咬不下去
that's the corn now
那這是現在的玉米
This is the old rice
這是以前的稻米
As soon as the bones grow up, they fall down
骨子一長起來就掉下去
just fall
就掉下去
fell into the water
就掉到水裡面去了
That's the current rice
那這是現在的米
that's wheat
那這是小麥
this is tomato
這是番茄
This former tomato is now a tomato
這以前的番茄現在的番茄
In the past, it was like a sunflower, like a small wild flower
以前的像日葵像小野花
Now it can be as big as a pot
現在可以像一個鍋子那麼大
So our jade seed scientists are very powerful
所以我們的玉種學家是很厲害的
These different crops can be
可以把這些不同的作物
make it into the present we can see
把它變成目前我們能看到
Such delicious food
這麼好吃的這些食物
So this is actually other than plants
那這個實際上除了植物之外呢
Where is our main line?
我們的主線呢
Also started to make this jade seed of many different plants
也開始做很多不同植物的這個玉種
This includes a lot of domestic animals
這個包括這個很多的家畜啦
Jiaqin
家琴啊
Then you see this home piano is very powerful
那你看這個家琴很厲害
the bird
這個鳥
There are many kinds of chicken
雞就可以有很多種
Pre-order a variety of different varieties like this
預出各種各樣不同的這樣子的品種
what about the animals
那動物呢
pig grows bigger
豬變大
From wild boar to domestic pig
從野豬變家豬變大
cow
牛呢
from bison great
從野牛很大
become a smaller cow
變成比較小的牛
etc. various
等等各種各樣的
that's great
那很厲害
Watching dogs can make such a big difference
看狗也是可以有這麼大的差異
big to small
很大到很小
It's all about taro seeds
這都是靠芋種
What about taro seeds?
那芋種呢
In fact, genes are constantly changing.
其實是基因是不斷的在發生改變的
Genetics are constantly mutating
遺傳在不斷的變異
At the same time, humans are also transforming their own experience.
那同時人類也在改造自己的經驗
We went from having to climb a tree to pick
我們從必須要爬到樹上去摘
banana start
香蕉開始
like a monkey
像猴子
Then slowly we can stand up
然後慢慢的我們可以站起來
can tear or something
可以拔裂什麼的
can work
可以工作
But because now Google
可不過因為現在有Google
Our people are starting to recover again
我們的人又開始恢復到
with our ancestors
跟我們祖先
almost
差不多啦
lie down again
又趴在
often mostly
常常大部分又
I often lie on this table again
常常又趴在這個桌子上
so what about humans
所以人類呢
also modifying our own genes
也在改造我們自己的基因
Are you going to get married and have kids?
會結婚生小孩嘛
Generations are different
一代一代就不一樣
OK
OK
ok then again
好 那再來呢
let's talk again
我們就再來講一下
Our Traditional Breeding Techniques
我們傳統的育種技術
Why can we seal the doctor's food
為什麼能夠讓我們封醫足食
Breeding?
育種呢
What about the crops of the natural world?
食尚自然界商的作物呢
it is likely to have a lot of variation
它很可能有很大的變異
like childbearing as an example
像以育女為例
it has
它有的呢
The bone ear is very big
就骨穗很大
some are very small
有的很小
so our ancestors were smart
所以我們的祖先很聰明
then start putting
那就開始把
What about the relatively large seed of encouragement?
這個比較大的這個鼓勵的種子呢
start to breed
就開始來繁殖
because in fact it's
因為實際上它這個
What about this Yumi package?
這個育米的這個包裹呢
big and small
有大有小
It has something to do with its genetic inheritance
就跟它的基因遺傳是有關係的
So after many generations
所以經過很多代
Such breeding should be selected
這樣的育種要選拔
now we can see
現在我們才能夠看到
Such an excellent rice variety
這麼優良的這個育米的品種
What about this evidence?
那這個證據呢
is in mohigan
是在莫希根
Because rice farming started from this side of Central America
因為育米是從這個中美洲那邊開始的
Nakanami
中南美
Yumi
育米
mohiganfa
莫希根發
Maize was discovered 7,000 years ago
發現玉米在七千年前
The fossils they dug up were so small
他們挖出來的化石是這麼小
Then it was discovered that the dug out was getting bigger and bigger
然後後來發現挖出來的越來越大
That is, as recently as five hundred years ago,
就是隨著到最近五百年前的時候
Already fossils have gotten so big
已經化石已經變得這麼大
so this is a proof
所以這是一個證據
It's the corn seed
它這個玉米的玉種
Let the size of this bone marrow continue to increase
讓它這個骨髓的尺寸不斷的變大
So the jade seed of corn actually comes from
所以玉米的玉種其實它從
Start this with many branches
開始這個有很多的分枝
The bone grains are few and hard
那骨粒也很少很硬
Until now its branches have become few
到現在它的分枝就變得很少
basically a trunk
基本上一個主幹
Then what about the corn produced
然後呢產生的玉米
This becomes a big bone
這個變得骨粒就變得很大
So reducing the branches increases the size of the bone grain
所以減少分枝增加骨粒的大小
So is the rice
那水稻也是一樣
This rice is a very important grain
這個稻米是很重要的糧食
Then our main fairy is very smart
那我們的主仙呢是很聰明
In this I just started talking about
在這個我剛才開始講說
The Lord Immortal breathes there
主仙在那裡鉛息啊
Then maybe take the day...
然後可能拿天...
to the water's edge
到水邊去
just see the water
就看到這個水裡面
grow a certain plant
有長某一個植物
Most other plants do not grow
別的植物大部分都不長
only it is long
只有它長
it has encouragement
它上面還長鼓勵
This is the origin of rice
這個是水稻的由來
But the encouragement at that time
可是那時候的鼓勵
fall off easily
很容易就掉下來
then fall into the water
然後就掉到水裡面去
to the plant itself
對植物本身來說
it is said that encouragement falls off easily
它是說鼓勵容易掉下來
it breeds easily
它就容易繁殖
Just now Vice President Wang also introduced
剛剛王副院長也有介紹
the rice seed
這個水稻的種子
able to germinate in water
能夠在水中發芽
is a very special phenomenon
是一個非常特殊的現象
Including corn, wheat, barley, sorghum, etc.
包括玉米小麥大麥高粱等等
those plants
那些植物
Seeds cannot germinate in water
種子都沒有辦法在水裡面發芽
rice is ok
水稻就是可以
It has such characteristics
它就有這樣子的特性
while our ancestors
而我們的祖先
Take advantage of this characteristic to grow rice
就利用這樣的特性來種水稻
Because it can control weeds
因為可以防除雜草
Most other plants are not tolerant to flooding
其他大部分的植物都不耐淹水
So my rice is planted in water
所以我這個水稻種在水裡面
i stand alone
我一隻毒秀
no one competes with me
沒有人跟我競爭
our ancestors
我們祖先
so why come to us
所以為什麼到我們
where are we now
我們現在呢
grow rice
種水稻
You can see the rice is still planted in this water
你可以看到水稻都還種在這個水裡面
Weed control is a big reason
防除雜草是一個很重要的原因
The main reason is not that rice really likes water
主要原因不是真正水稻喜歡水
Water actually has some effect on root growth
水其實對根的生長還是有一些影響
So during certain growing periods
所以在某些生長的時期呢
It makes the rice grow well
它要讓水稻長得好
it drains the water
它要把水排掉
But usually it makes it flood
可是平常它讓它淹水
Because it can control weeds
是因為可以防除雜草
This way you don't need to spend artificial weeding
這樣你就不需要去花人工除草
Or sprinkle this weed spray
或是還要灑這個沙草劑
Because weed is expensive
因為沙草劑很貴
Weed spray is the world's
沙草劑是全世界上
In the chemicals used in agriculture
所用農業上面所用的化學藥劑裡面
most
量最多的
That rice has this benefit
那水稻有這個好處
But the disadvantage is that
可是缺點就是說
You're going to go if you're so familiar with it.
你這個骨子一層熟去就要去啦
you can really receive
你真的能夠收到的
there is not much to eat
就能夠吃的就沒有多少
So what about our taro seeds?
所以我們芋種呢
In the end it will be able to grow into this rice
最後它能夠裕成這個稻米呢
Its bone grains are tightly combined with the rice fragments
它這個骨粒就緊緊的結合在這個稻碎上面
not easy to drop
就不容易掉
Then it's easy for us
那這樣子我們就很容易
Good for our harvest
有利於我們的採收
Okay, what about Mr. Yu, for thousands of years
好 那郁總呢 這麼幾千年來
Going west is a very complicated process
西上他是一個很複雜的過程
Then we use this IR
那這個我們以這個 IR
The Philippine International Pirate Research Center
這個菲律賓國際盜民研究中心
They yu come out IR 64
他們郁出來 IR 64
From this breed
這一個品種來看
we don't need much explanation
我們不需要太了解說
What does the eyebrows mean?
這裡面眉部 眉部什麼意思
but he meant
可是他意思是說
he has many ancestors
他有很多的祖先
Then each of these frames is an ancestor
那這些每一個框框都是一個祖先
his mother father
他的母本 父本
Then he goes to crossbred
然後他去做雜交
After this is handed over to this
這個跟這個交了以後
offspring with another
後代又跟另外一個交
so don't pay
所以就不趟的交
What about the hybridization process?
那在這個雜交的過程呢
Elites will mutate
菁英會有突變
there will be missing
會有缺失
there will be reorganization
會有重組
He keeps changing
他就不斷的一直在改變
So he later encountered these waterway species
所以他後來遇出來這些水道品種
With this ancestor all already have appearance above
跟這個祖先都已經有外觀上面
Many agronomic traits above
很多的農藝性狀上面
have very different characteristics.
都已經有非常不一樣的特性了
Therefore, Mr. Yu, a human being, has been
所以人類郁總已經就一直在
Constantly changing the elite of this plant
不斷的改變這個植物的菁英
This particle is the taro seed of this wheat
這個粒子是這個小麥的芋種
The different strains of wheat it compares to each other
那不同的品系的小麥它彼此之間
Sorry, this is Brosica
對不起 這個是Brosica
This is the cruciferous vegetable
這個是那個十字花科的這個蔬菜
In this particle, that is
以這個粒子就是說
If you AA this breed
如果你AA這個品種
Crossbreed with the BB breed
跟BB這個品種雜交
its offspring becomes ab
它的後代變成AB
Then I mean cross BB with CC and it becomes BC
然後我是說BB跟CC雜交它變成BC
have such characteristics
有這樣子的特性
So after crossing your chromosome
所以雜交之後你的這個染色體
it will start to mix
它就會開始混合
what's more
那更有甚者呢
Because our taro breeders also know that
因為我們的芋種學家也知道說
increased number of chromosomes
染色體的數目增加
These can often make your output come out of these
往往可以使你的這個產出來的這些
bone or fruit
骨子或是果子
its size will increase
它的大小會變大
So it figured out how to make its gene body bigger
所以它把它想辦法讓它的基因體變大
Then it may be three different main lines
那它就有可能是三個不同來的主線
it just mixes it up
它就把它混在一起
or the same genetic
或是說同一個遺傳的
it doubles it and triples it
它把它加倍變成三倍
All sorts of ways this genetics can be used to do
種種的這種利用這遺傳的方法可以做
So what about wheat? What about current wheat?
所以小麥呢 目前的小麥呢
What about its genetics?
它的這個遺傳呢
It can have the shape of three sets of chromosomes like this
就可以有這樣子三套染色體這樣子的形狀
Then we just mentioned that
那我們剛剛有提到說
Corn is being bred and it's encouraged to grow bigger
玉米在育種呢 它的鼓勵變大
why
為什麼呢
That's because breeders know that
那是因為育種學家知道說
hybrid vigor
雜交優勢
Then we humans are always like this
那我們人類也常這樣子
sometimes respectful breeding
有時候敬親繁殖
You will feel that there may be some bad shape coming out
你會覺得可能有一些不好的形狀就出來了
So the more distant genetics
所以那比較遠的遺傳因子
If you are far away and come here to get married
比較遠的你來這個結婚的話
It's possible to be smarter after having a baby
生下小孩子 是有可能比較聰明一點
Said that when I was in high school
說我以前在念高中念書的時候
Our relic teacher talks to us all day long
我們那聖物老師一天到晚都跟我們講說
if you are taiwanese
如果你是台灣人
You'd better marry someone from the Northeast in the future
你將來最好嫁東北人
Xinjiang people or something
新疆人什麼之類的
Advocate with us all day long
一天到晚跟我們鼓吹
Then he really insisted on genetic warfare
那他真的維持說遺傳系戰
it may be possible
越演可能可以
Can have offspring that will be better
可以有出來後代會比較優秀
So this can be seen
所以這個可以看出來
This corn, this A and B
這個玉米這個A跟B
It turns out that one may be the father and the other may be the mother.
原來這個一個可能是父親一個是母親
After he crossed
他一雜交之後
No matter how you hand over the seeds of his offspring
無論你怎麼交他的後代的種子
become bigger
都變得比較大
After the seeds grow bigger, after the encouragement grows bigger
種子變大以後 鼓勵變大以後
The farmer's harvest began to increase
農民他的收穫就開始增加了
So what about this upgrade company?
所以這個升級公司呢
He started selling the offspring
他就開始賣這個後代
his offspring
他的雜交以後的後代
It is really better if the offspring are encouraged.
那這個後代就是鼓勵就真的比較好
But farmers can't breed by themselves
可是農民自己沒辦法繁殖
because after you reproduce yourself
因為你自己繁殖以後
What about his offspring?
他的那個後代呢
Bad shape at the beginning will reappear
開始不好的形狀又會出現
So what about this agricultural upgrading company in many international markets?
所以在很多國際間這個農業升級公司呢
They're selling this hybrid seed
他們在賣這個雜交種子
he makes money from it
他靠這個賺錢
He hybridized himself in the company
他自己在公司裡面雜交
and sell the hybrid seed to farmers
然後賣給農民這個雜交的種子
Farmers breed themselves
農民自己繁殖呢
This seed is getting worse
這個種子就越來越差
This is the characteristic of corn
這個是玉米有這樣的特性
Because it is required for heterosis
因為它是需要雜種優勢
Then we usually grow rice by ourselves
那我們平常農民自己種稻子
Needless to say
比較不需要說
I've been buying hybrid seeds
一直要去買雜交種子
Because rice self-fertilizes
因為稻子自己自交
Its offspring can still grow well
它的後代還是可以長得不錯
but actually hybrid
可是實際上雜交
even rice
即使是連稻子
Its hybrid still has an advantage
它的雜交還是有優勢
So on the mainland they are now
所以大陸上他們現在
What about this hybrid rice?
這個雜交稻呢
is very popular now
現在是非常流行的
Because the output increased so much
因為產量增加非常的多
It can be increased by more than 20 to 30%
可以增加二、三十%以上
OK
OK
so what about farmers
所以農民呢
I have to deal with this biotech company
只好都跟這個生技公司
go buy this seed
去買這個種子
Although more expensive
雖然比較貴
cost money
要花錢
But because of its high yield
可是因為它的產量高
So what about the statistics?
所以它這個統計呢
I mean it came out in 1935
是說從1935年出來
There is hybrid rice between 60 and
有雜交稻到60年之間呢
The hybrid rice planted by this farmer
這個農民種的這個雜交稻的
The area is getting higher and higher
面積越來越高
because it can make money
因為它可以賺錢
good
好
OK
OK
Then let's come again, as mentioned earlier
那我們再來剛剛前面有提到
Around 1960 to 2000
在1960到2000年左右
Our population has almost tripled
我們的人口增加了差不多是兩倍
There is a very important reason for that
那有一個很重要的原因是
What about that period?
那時候那一段期間呢
food has almost tripled
糧食也幾乎差不多也是增加了兩倍
That great contribution is the two scholars
那很大的貢獻是兩位學者
One is Noven Borla
一個是Noven Borla
The other one is our Academician Zhang Deci
那另外一位是我們的張德慈院士
What about Noven, he is the boss of wheat
那Noven呢他是做小麥的御總
Academician Zhang Deci is the chief executive who makes rice
那張德慈院士是做稻米的御總
Where's the time for their boss?
他們的御總的時間呢
In fact, it was about that time
其實是差不多那一段時間的
What a pity for this Westerner
那可惜這個西方人呢
always have an advantage in the comparison
總是常常會在比較佔優勢
they won the nobel prize
他們他得了諾貝爾獎
But what about Academician Zhang?
可是張院士呢
It's a pity I didn't get the Nobel Prize
就很可惜沒有得到諾貝爾獎
So yesterday Ang Lee won the best director
所以昨天李安得這個最佳導演
He is also very emotional
他也很感慨
We orientals often have a lot of actors
我們東方人常常很多的演員
are very good
都非常的優秀
inside this boy pie
這個少年派裡面
That indian guy really did a really good job
那個印度男生真的演得非常好
no awards were proposed
什麼獎都沒有被提出來
So the orientals are often at a disadvantage here
所以東方人常常在這邊比較吃虧
Academician Zhang is still a pity
張院士他還是很可惜
Fortunately, there were many awards later.
可是還好後來有很多的這個獎
Vatican Third World
凡蒂岡 第三世界
Then this has something like this and finally has this
然後這個有很像這個最後有這個
taylor award or something
泰勒獎什麼的
In the end, they gave him a lot of honors.
都最後給他很多的這個殊榮
ok, what about their type of bath?
ok 那他們這個浴種呢
The most important thing is that he made this wheat and corn
最重要的是他讓這一個小麥跟玉米的
height reduction
高度降低
Why can the output be improved
為什麼能夠產量能夠提高
First
第一個
when he grows too tall
他長得太高的時候
is his nutrition
就就是他的營養
Much of his energy wasted on him
他的很多的能源浪費掉他
wasted in his constant vegetative reproduction
浪費在他不斷的營養繁殖
Then he won't understand
那他就不解種
so you waste energy
所以你能源浪費掉
so you don't let him be so high
所以你不要讓他那麼高
It can use a lot of energy on the seeds
它就可以把很多的能量用在種子上面
Besides, it's a little shorter
另外它矮一點呢
It will have more branches
它的分支也會比較多
Like rice and wheat
對稻米跟小麥這樣子
So its output will also increase
所以呢它的產量也會提高
that in addition
那另外
In fact, the first green revolution
其實第一次綠色革命呢
Except for this dwarf variety
除了這個矮化品種
the breed itself
品種本身
Another feature is that
另外一個特點就是說
because we are doing
因為我們在做
We all need to be wet and fat when we are doing crops
做物的時候我們都要濕肥
Especially egg fat is very much needed
尤其是蛋肥是很需要的
can increase its output
可以增加它的產量
But you are getting fatter
可是你蛋肥一加呢
Rice is a plant that grows faster
稻子就是植物長得更快
higher
更高
It's easy to fall like this
這樣子就很容易倒伏
so you can see how tall it is
所以你可以看它原來這麼高
getting so short now
現在變得這麼矮
It's easier to fall
就是比較不容易倒伏
So what about after it is short?
所以呢它矮了以後呢
You can fatten up a little more
你就可以多一點蛋肥下去
So it can increase its output
所以可以提高它的產量
So what about these two crops?
所以這個兩個作物呢
are very similar
都非常的像
very similar method
非常類似的方法
that's it
就這樣預成了
that's important
那很重要
this in several countries
這個在幾個國家上
or an indian
或是個印度
This is a lot of people
這個都是人口很多的
The original food is not enough
原來的這個糧食都不夠的
But he planted this
可是他種了這個
After half-milk wheat
半奶性的小麥之後呢
In fact, after the crop dwarfs,
其實像這個作物變矮以後
Its disease resistance will also be improved
它的抗病性也是會比較提高的
What about its output?
它的這個產量呢
improved a lot
就提高得非常的多
Since it originally had to import food
從它原來必須要輸入糧食
become it able to output this food
變成它能夠輸出這個糧食
so this is the first time
所以這是第一次
A very important contribution of the green revolution
綠色革命的一個很重要的貢獻
So is the rice
那這個稻米也是一樣
So in this paragraph
所以在這一段
The period from 1960 to 2000
1960年到2000年這一段的時間
double the population
人口加倍
From 3 billion to 6 billion
從30億到60億
Rice production is also
稻米的產量也是從
You see this is double this
你看這個也是這個加倍
2 to 4 this
2到4這個
every year to every stew
每年到每燉
The amount that can be produced per project
每工程可以產生的量
Academician Zhang
那張院士
what is he doing amazingly
他做得了不起的是什麼
This special waterway in Taiwan
台灣的這個特殊的這個水道
low foot stain fried
叫低腳污煎
take it to the philippines
拿到菲律賓去
Hybridized with this local waterway in the Philippines
跟菲律賓當地的這個水道雜交
pre-out this IR-8
預出來這個IR-8
IR-8
IR-8號
this rice
這一個稻米
Known as Miracle Rice
被稱為神奇稻米
because of its output
因為它的產量
just make it double like this
就是可以讓它這樣子加倍
So this one is very famous
所以呢這個是非常有名的
This is a species of waterway
這個一個水道的品種
that's amazing
那很了不起
The whole world knows that it is from Taiwan
全世界上都知道說是台灣來的
low foot stain fried
低腳污煎
So also like our Director Ang Lee
所以也像我們李安導演一樣
Sell ​​Taiwan to countries all over the world
把我們台灣推銷到世界各國
OK
OK
So during this period of the Green Revolution
所以這一段綠色革命的期間
You can see that the population is actually increasing
你可以看到人口其實是增加
it this
它這個
Different colors refer to different states
不同的顏色是指不同的州
We can start by marking which state
我們可以先標管是哪一州
Asia is the most
亞洲是最多
The population is increasing the most
人口這是增加最多的
The population increased by one hundred percent
人口增加了百分之百
Food has also increased by more than one hundred percent
糧食也增加了超過百分之百
But the cultivated area
可是耕種的面積
In fact, you can see that the line is very slow
其實你可以看它這個線很緩
Is this right? It’s faster to climb uphill than this one.
對不對 這個比較爬坡爬得比較快
this is very calm
這個就很平緩
It only increases the cultivated area by 20 percent
它只 耕種的面積只增加百分之二十
So it means the output of grain per unit area
所以意思是說單位面積的糧食的產量
increased very much
增加得非常的多
Then this is its species
那這個是就是它這個品種
great place
厲害的地方
OK, let's finish this traditional breeding
OK 那我們講完這個傳統育種
let's talk
我們就來講一下
How does modern breeding work
現代的育種是怎麼做的
What about modern molecular breeding?
那現代分子的育種呢
allows us to increase efficiency
可以讓我們提高效率
it combines molecular biology
它要結合分子生物
and tissue culture
還有組織培養
Then there's the part-time job
然後還要填兼的工作
so breeding
所以育種呢
It's not that modern technology
其實不是說有現代的科技
Tradition is gone
傳統就都不要了
In fact, we still have to solve it now
實際上現在都還是要解
together
在一起
We have produced many varieties in the laboratory
我們在實驗室裡面做出來很多的品種
to plant in the field
要種到田裡面去
still rely on many agronomists in the field
還是要靠很多田裡面的農藝學家
Specologists come and continue to help us
域種學家來繼續幫我們
care for and reproduce these offspring
照顧繁殖這些後代
Then this technological progress
那這個科技進步
Advances in molecular biotechnology are very important
分子生物技術進步是非常的重要的
because each of us
因為我們每一
including human animals or this crop
包括人類動物或是這個作物
we have a genotype
我們有一個基因型
That is to say, inside our chromosomes
就是說我們的染色體裡面
have a lot of genes
有很多的基因
So it will determine our phenotype
所以它會決定我們的表現型
Decide what we'll look like when the time comes
決定我們到時候表現出來是什麼樣子
So everyone's genes are a little bit different
所以每一個人基因多少都有一點不同
So the length is not the same
所以長的就都不太一樣
but in
可是在
you have to tell
你要來辨別說
Which gene causes which phenotype
哪一個基因造成什麼樣的表現型
Genotype is relatively easy to use scientific methods to identify
基因型是比較容易用科學的方法去鑑定的
Phenotyping is more difficult
表現型是比較難的
because this
因為這個
just say one parent
不同就說一個父母
Just say a mom and dad
就說一個爸爸媽媽
You know the baby you gave birth to
生下的小孩子你也知道
gave birth to three children five children
生下三個小孩子 五個小孩子
Everyone basically looks different
每一個人基本上還是長得不太一樣
less likely to say exactly the same
比較不可能說完全一樣
besides being twins
除了是雙胞胎
So, genes are complicated
所以呢 基因是很複雜的
just a little difference
只要有一點差別
Then he's likely to come out with a different phenotype.
那他很可能出來的表現型就不一樣
so we
所以呢 我們
but for us
可是對我們來說
we grow crops in the field
我們在田裡面種作物呢
phenotype is important
表現型是重要的
I just need my good breed
我就是需要我這個好的品種
looks like this
長得就是這個樣子
the output is so high
產量就是這麼高
it is so delicious
就是這麼好吃
and you
那你
But your descendants are swollen and swollen
可是你這個後代 淋淋腫腫的
After his father and mother interbreed with his mother
他爸爸媽媽跟媽媽雜交之後
how do i know who is good
我怎麼知道誰是好
who is bad
誰是壞
So what about molecular biology?
所以呢 分子生物呢
just let us
就可以讓我們
Help us do this breeding
輔助我們來做這個育種
Let's take an example
那我們舉個例子來說
There is a variety of tomato
有一個番茄的品種
it is a very good variety
它是很優良的品種
may have large fruit
可能果實很大
high output
產量很高
but it is not disease resistant
可是它不抗病
there's a bad breed in the wild
那有一個野生不好的品種
Or people don't pay much attention to his breed
或大家不太理他的品種
He actually has a disease resistance gene
實際上他卻帶有一個抗病基因
So our
所以我們這個
his chromosomes
他的染色體
We now use different colors to represent
我們現在就用不同的顏色來代表
And this bad tomato
而這個不好的這個番茄
disease resistance gene
他帶有的抗病基因
It's the yellow one
就是黃色這一條
it's his genes
就是他帶有的基因
So what do we want to do with his good genes?
那我們想把他這個好的基因呢
disease resistance gene
抗病基因
Lead to this excellent tomato variety
導到這個優良的番茄品種上面
we are going to interbreed
我們就要去雜交
What about after hybridization?
一雜交以後呢
There will be many descendants
後代就非常的多了
of various ages
年齡種種的
then you don't know
然後呢你就不曉得
Who is really carrying this disease resistance gene?
誰才是真正帶有這個抗病基因的
what about that
那要怎麼樣
how to distinguish
怎麼樣子去分辨
But of course you have someone to say
可是你當然有人會說
When you are in the field, you vaccinate him.
你在田裡面你就給他接種嘛
Just sprinkle a bunch of sick bacteria on it.
把一堆病人菌就灑上去了
and see who survives
然後看看誰活下來
But sometimes we don't like it
可是有時候我們不太喜歡這樣做啦
Because we are in the field
因為我們田裡面
We're all terrified of these sick germs
我們都很怕有這些病人菌
You're going to scatter a bunch of sick germs down there again.
你又要撒一大堆病人菌下去
That patient's bacteria will never end in the future
那個病人菌就以後就沒完沒了
So now there is a more scientific way to do
所以現在就有更科學的方法來做
The most important thing is that after hybridization of this breed
最主要是這個品種雜交之後
its descendants
它的後代
we can all say this
這個我們都可以說
its different offspring
它不同的後代
Some people have the gene of this father
有的人就有帶有這個爸爸來的基因
disease resistance gene
抗病的基因
there is no
有的就沒有
Some have mother's genes
有的帶有媽媽的基因
But you can see it has different combinations
可是你可以看它有不同的組合
So how do I tell who is good?
那我怎麼去區別誰是好的呢
Then we're going to use this genetic marker to filter
那我們就要用這個基因標記來篩選
This disease-resistant spider
這個抗病的這個蜘蛛
the molecular biology approach
那分子生物的方法
allows us to judge
可以讓我們判斷
every plant
每一顆植物
who has our disease resistance genes
它誰帶有我們抗病的基因
Then I put it with
然後呢我就把它跟
this one good this one mom
這一個好的這一個媽媽
or this species
或是說好的這個品種
We keep backcrossing and backcrossing
我們不斷的一直回交一直回交
Of course humans can't do that.
當然人類不太能這樣做啦
But plants can
可是植物是可以的
We can go back and forth
我們可以不斷的去回交
take it this one
把它這一個
This gene from a bad breed
來自於不好品種的這個基因
dilute until then
到時候一直稀釋掉
diluted to the end
稀釋到最後都沒有了
Then only this disease resistance gene remains
然後只有這個抗病基因留下來
Everything else is the gene of this good breed
其他的都是這個好的品種來的基因
so what
所以呢
This is still using our current technology
這個還是用我們現在科技的方法
This can now be accelerated
現在可以加快這個速度
But when there was no such method before
可是以前沒有這個方法的時候呢
A lot of them are really groping in the field.
真的是很多都是在田裡面摸索的
So it takes a very long time
所以需要花的時間非常的長
Likely five years, seven years, eight years, ten years
很可能是五年七年八年十年
But now we are really at the time of everyone's food
可是我們現在真的是大家糧食的時候
Really need fear
真的需求恐懼啊
Sometimes it feels like five or ten years is really a long wait
有時候覺得五年十年真的等很久
Then use the method now
那現在用現在這樣的方法
About three to five years
大概是差不多三年到五年
A good variety can be predicted
就可以預出來一個好的品種
much faster
速度加快很多
That's why
那也因為這樣子
But what about this molecular biology approach?
可是這種分子生物的方法呢
How can we
我們要怎麼樣子能夠
How about identifying its genotype?
辨識它的基因型呢
We need to understand its entire genetic structure
我們需要了解它整個的基因裡面的構造
So many works
所以呢很多的作品
like strawberry grapes, cotton, papaya
像草莓葡萄、棉花、木瓜
There are also jade mud, snow rice, soybeans like this
還有像這個玉泥、雪稻、大豆
This rapeseed waits for many trees
這個油菜等等很多的樹
Now its genes are slowly being unraveled
現在它這個基因都慢慢的都被解出來的
So we're doing this molecular bath
所以就對我們在做這種分子浴腫
help will be great
幫忙就會非常的大
OK, so this is a traditional bath swelling
OK 好 那這個是傳統浴腫
Combining some techniques of modern molecular biology
結合了一些現代分子生物學的技術
But basically there's no genetic engineering involved
可是基本上還沒有牽涉到基因工程
None of the stuff we just talked about has been genetically engineered.
我們剛剛講的那些都還沒有基因工程
But the method just mentioned
可是剛剛講的那方法
It still takes a little longer
需要的時間還是覺得長了一點
That flower is still a bit more labor-intensive
那花的人工還是多了一點
So it's time to move on to this genetically engineered swelling technique
所以就該更進展到這個基因工程浴腫的技術
It can improve efficiency and accuracy
它可以提高效率、精確度也比較高
that's safer
那也比較具安全性
We will talk about this later
這個我們後面會再慢慢的說
As we said just now, there is this excellent tomato variety
像剛剛我們說有個這個優良的番茄品種
That bad tomato variety has this disease-resistant gene.
那跟這個不好的番茄品種可是帶有這個抗病的基因
Now our molecular biology only needs me to know what kind of gene this gene is
現在我們的分子生物學只要我知道說這個基因是什麼基因呢
I have a way to copy it out
我就有辦法把它複製出來
and insert it into this variety
然後把它插到這個品種裡面
At present, most people plug in at will.
那現在目前大部分人插是隨意插進去
But it doesn't matter as long as you don't destroy its original important genes
可是只要你沒有破壞它原來重要的基因都沒有關係
But technology is constantly improving
可是技術現在不斷的進步
Now there are technologies that can be very accurate
現在已經有些技術可以非常的準確
Where am I on the chromosome
我在染色體上面的什麼位置
I want to insert it in that position
我要就插到那個位置
I know that location has the influence of this plant is the most
我知道那個位置都有這個植物的影響是最
can do this now
現在都可以做到這一點
So this is the genetic engineering method
所以呢這是基因工程方法
It can do this very efficiently and accurately.
它就可以很有效率很準確的來做這件事情
Because of our traditional method of hybridization
因為我們傳統的那種雜交方法
It will bring a lot of bad genes
它會把很多不好的基因都帶過來
So you have to keep crossing back
所以你要不斷地一直回交
take a long time
要經過很長的時間
But often in the end
可是常常到最後呢
still have a little gene
還是有那麼一點點的基因
you can't help it maybe bad genes
你沒辦法可能不太好的基因
not easy to rule it out
不太容易把它排除
Often there will still be such problems
往往還是會有那樣子的問題
But now we have a very precise method
可是現在我們很精確的方法
You can avoid this problem by inserting
插進去就可以避免這個問題
what's another advantage
那還有一個優點是什麼
We know that there are many types of this grain
我們知道這個糧食的種類非常的多
From fruits, vegetables, bones, beans, etc.
從水果、蔬菜、骨類、豆類等等
there are so many different crops
有這麼多不同的作物
In fact, there are often some genes
那其實常常有些基因
good genes like
好的基因譬如說
As I just said, I am so watery that I have a gene for resistance to flooding
我剛剛講的我水到有一個耐淹水的基因
But other bone types are not submerged
可是其他的骨類都不耐淹水
Can I put my gene in corn
我可不可以把我這個基因放到玉米裡面
put in the wheat
放到小麥裡面
no
不行
because they can't fry
因為他們不能炸澆
but we will know
可是我們將來知道
what kind of gene is this
這一個什麼樣的基因
Can control this apricot after
可以控制這個杏狀之後
I can turn water into the flood tolerance gene
我可以把水到耐淹水的基因
do put
做放到
corn or wheat
玉米或是小麥裡面
That corn is more drought-resistant than baby corn
那玉米跟小玉米它比較抗旱
it can have a gene for drought resistance
它可以有一個抗旱的基因
we can put it in the waterway
我們可以把它放到水道裡面
Relying on traditional jade seed hybridization is not enough
靠傳統的玉種雜交也不行
Because different species can't interbreed
因為不同種嘛 不能雜交
So I rely on the method of molecular biology
所以呢我靠分子生物的方法
I can put the drought tolerance gene in corn
我可以把玉米的抗旱基因
I put it in the waterway
我就放到水道裡面
That doesn't matter
那這個沒有什麼關係啊
Although people say that you are artificial
雖然人家說啊你這是人工的
You mix this gene like this
你把這個基因這樣子混合
Will there be any problems in nature
會不會對自然界中有什麼問題
Actually it's okay
其實沒什麼問題啦
look at us
你看我們啊
Anyway, these grains are eaten in the stomach
反正這些糧食吃到肚子裡面
It's all mixed together, right?
都混在一起啦 對不對
No matter where you came from
管你原來是什麼哪裡來的
So you are from wheat
原來你是小麥來的
From corn to vegetables
玉米來的蔬菜來的
In our stomach
我們肚子裡面本來就
There are a lot of different grains under finance
就金融下一大堆不同的這些糧食了
It doesn't matter if it's mixed in the stomach
混在肚子裡面也沒什麼關係
More importantly, it will be digested at all
更重要是根本都會消化掉
no matter what food you eat
不論不論你吃的是什麼食物
it digests you absorb it
它就消化掉你就吸收掉了
So this gene of this different species
所以呢這個不同種的這個基因
It's actually a good thing to exchange like this
不相這樣交換 其實是好事
That is also true for this natural world
那也對這個自然界中
It doesn't matter too much.
也沒什麼太大影響嘛
As we said earlier
我們前面一開始已經說
The human race is already a lot of genes
人類遇種已經就是很多的基因
I've been messing around like this
就已經這樣子弄來弄去了
OK let's give an example
OK 那我們舉個例子
with this genetic engineering method
用這個基因工程方法
what can we do
我們可以做些什麼事情
in africa
在非洲呢
This bacterial tail vulture disease
這個細菌尾雕性的病害
is very serious
是非常嚴重的
Farmers often don't get the bananas
農民呢 往往都收不到這個香蕉
Bananas in countries like Africa
香蕉在非洲這種國家
is an important food crop
是很重要的一個糧食作物
If so
那這樣子的話
I was already short of food
本來已經很缺糧了
That's going to make me hungry
那更要餓肚子了
What about the bacteria?
那它這個細菌呢
After you cut the fungus
你把它這個菌切開以後
you can see
你可以看到
stay with this sticky thing
這個黏黏的東西留下來
this is bacteria
這就是細菌
So it's a terrible disease
所以是很可怕的病
no good treatment
沒什麼太好的治療的方法
Traditional encounters are also very limited
傳統遇種也做得很有限
But now I know that green peppers contain
可是現在知道說青椒裡面
there is this chili inside
有這個辣椒裡面
There is a gene that is resistant to this disease
有一個基因是可以抗這個病害的
So put it in this banana
所以就把它放到這個香蕉裡面
Look no, then go get vaccinated
你看沒有然後去接種
Of course, this is done in a laboratory or a greenhouse.
這個當然在實驗室或是溫室裡面做
It turns out that once you are vaccinated with this species, you are sightseeing.
原來這個品種你一接種就是觀光了
But this one has the gene from the pepper
可是這一個有從辣椒來的基因
it can grow well
它可以長得好好的
So this is a great one for genetic engineering
所以這是基因工程一個很厲害的一個
a contribution
一個貢獻
so now in africa
所以現在在非洲
Bananas like this have already started
這樣子的香蕉已經開始
They are evaluating whether it is possible for farmers to plant
他們在評估是不是可以能夠讓農民來種
Another example
另外還有一個例子
It is an antibacterial virus using this thule bacteria
是利用這個蘇利菌的抗菌病毒
antimicrobial protein we should talk about antimicrobial protein
抗菌蛋白我們應該講抗菌蛋白
Suriella is a bacterium
蘇利菌是一個細菌
In fact it is in our
其實它在我們
It has been used in agriculture for a long time
農業上面用了很久了
It has been used for decades
已經用了幾十年了
because it kills a lot of that
因為它會殺很多那種
Insects like this
臨次牧的這樣的昆蟲
Insects like many oysters and butterflies
像很多這個蚵蝶這一類的這個昆蟲
will harm the forest
會傷害森林
What about in the forest?
那森林裡面呢
You're less likely to get sprayed sometimes
你不太有時候不太可能去噴藥了
Because the cost is too high
因為實在是成本太高了
and sometimes limited
而且有時候效果有限
that could hurt a lot
那又可能傷到很多
the hesitant animals
這個猶豫的這些動物
So Suriella is used in this forest
所以蘇利菌用在這個森林裡面
I used to be a biological house
以前就做生物房子
It's been a long time
已經就用很久了
Then people who grow organic vegetables now
然後現在種有機蔬菜的人
Actually used a lot
其實也用了很多
he is on top of his vegetables
他在他的蔬菜上面
on top of the fruits and vegetables
就蔬果上面
He still kills Suriella
他還是會殺蘇利菌
Really ask this organic heavier person to know
真的去問這個有機更重的人就知道
Those biotech companies
那這個幾個生技公司
They took a gene in this suri bacterium
他們就把這個蘇利菌裡面的一個基因
this gene it is to a
這個基因它是到一個
insect-resistant protein
抗蟲的蛋白
it puts it in this corn
它把它放到這個玉米裡面
you can see this corn
你可以看到這個玉米
Without doing genetic engineering like this
如果沒有這樣子做基因工程
This insect is very powerful
這個蟲是非常的厲害的
It's easy to destroy this corn just like that
很容易把這個玉米就這樣毀掉
it just takes a few bites
它只要咬幾口
Farmers can't sell
農民就賣不出去了
OK
OK
so what
所以呢
The protein produced by this green machine
這個蘇綠機產生的蛋白
what kind of protein
是一個什麼樣子的蛋白
it this is its bacteria
它這個是它的細菌
visible under a microscope
在顯微鏡底下可以看到
Seen under a high powered microscope
高倍的顯微鏡底下看到
traditional method
傳統的方法
You just put this threophyte
你就是把這個蘇綠菌
sprinkled on the surface of the leaves
灑在葉片的表面
current genetic engineering methods
現在基因工程的方法
is to let the plant itself produce this protein
是讓植物本身來產生這個蛋白
insects eat
昆蟲就吃了
eat into the stomach
吃到腸胃裡面
either way
不論哪一種方法
it eats into the stomach
它吃進去到腸胃裡面
the insect
這個昆蟲
Insects like Lin Akagi
林赤木這樣的昆蟲
There are some skinny in its stomach
它的腸胃裡面有一些瘦
Its body will bind to this protein
它這個壽體它就會結合這個蛋白
Then its stomach will be perforated by it
然後它的腸胃就會被它穿孔
So the insect's stomach and intestines are perforated
所以這昆蟲的肚子那個腸就穿孔了
so why does this insect die
所以為什麼這個昆蟲就會死了
Then its life body is a very special life body
那它這個壽體是非常特別的一個壽體
not all insects have
不是所有的昆蟲都有
Mainly because of the red wood insects
主要就是臨赤木昆蟲有
Then our people will not have such a life
然後我們的人更是不會有這樣子的壽體
So it's harmless to people
所以對人是無害的
So why biocontrol
所以為什麼生物防治上面
the reason it takes so long
會用這麼久的原因
So those biotech companies
所以那些生技公司
It puts this gene into this plant
它就把這個基因放到這個植物裡面
let it produce itself
讓它自己去生產
That way you don't have to spray
這樣的話你就不用去噴
Because if you spray it, you still need to feed the bacteria
因為去噴你還要養這個細菌
Then you have to spray it manually
然後還要人工去噴
It takes energy and manpower
又要花能源 花人力
Then another one has a potential problem
然後另外一個有一個潛在的問題
Many people like organic vegetables and think they are safe
很多人喜歡有機蔬菜認為就很安全
Just wash and wash
隨洗一洗就行了
In fact, there may be a lot of bacteria still attached to it.
其實可能很多的細菌還附在這上面
because of U.S
因為我們
We usually cook this food
我們通常是煮過的這個食物
in order to be able to truly completely sterilize
才能夠真正完全殺菌
So sometimes you spray the bacteria directly
所以有時候你直接噴這個細菌
not necessarily a good thing
也不見得是一個好事
But this protein
可是產生這個蛋白
This is proved by experiments
這個都是經過實驗證明說
It is low enough that it is not harmful to humans
它的量夠低不會對人危害
But it's enough to kill the insect
可是它又足以殺死這個昆蟲
So this product in this genetic engineering
所以這個在這個基因工程的這個產品
to be listed
才能夠上市
So it was very successful on corn
所以在玉米上面是非常的成功
This genetic modification of us is called a gene
這個基因改造的我們叫做基因
Corn is not genetic
玉米這個不是基因的
This is the blade just is it's into the blade
這是葉片剛剛是它的進葉片
Then wrap it in this broken piece
然後裹是它的這個碎
for farmers
對農民來說
It is really expensive to buy this seed
去買這個種子的確是比較貴
but its harvest is good
可是它的收成好
Okay so that means he can make money
好 所以代表他可以賺錢
So why actually plant this genetically engineered plant like this
所以為什麼其實種這樣子的這個基因工程的這個
The country of these products
這個這些產品的國家
In fact, more and more farmers
農民其實是越來越多
we'll come back later
我們待會還會再提
what good does he do
那他有什麼好處呢
Like this one that itself will resist insects
像這種自己本身會抗蟲的這個
What are the benefits of genetic crops
基因的作物有什麼好處
Then there are many people who say
那有很多人就在單一說
especially environmental groups
尤其是環保團體
I have always been very opposed to a product like this
一直都是非常反對於這樣子的一個產品
But this is in Australia
可是這是在澳洲
They were in 1993 and 1994
他們在93、94年
I think he is starting to do
我看他是開始做
This dotted line is the genetic cotton
這個虛線是基因的棉花
He started in 1996 and 1997 to 2002 and 2003
他在96、97年開始到02、03年
During the 56 years
在56年的期間
He went to see the amount of pesticide used
他去看這個使用的農藥的量
So to achieve this one is the traditional cotton
所以實現這一條是傳統的棉花
The following is genetic cotton
下面這個是基因的棉花
Its usage is reduced by one-third to one-half
它的用量減少三分之一到二分之一
This is a very significant difference
這個是非常顯著的差別
It's just Australia
這個還只是澳洲一個國家
In fact, there are many countries in the world
其實全世界現在有非常多的國家
a lot of crops
種非常多的作物
These are the crops now
現在都是這一類的作物
Think about how much that pesticide can be reduced
你想想看那個農藥可以減少多少
OK this is cotton
OK 這是棉花
And then there are often people who object to memories
然後另外就常常有人就會反對記憶們
He said this is for those in the field
他說這個對田裡面的
Intentional insects are socially harmful
有意的昆蟲生社會有害
because a deliberate insect is likely to eat you this
因為有意的昆蟲很可能吃了你這個
Resistant corn
抗蟲的玉米啊
cotton or this soybean
棉花或是這個大豆
This intentional insect will die
這個有意昆蟲就會死
So this experiment was done in mainland China
所以這個實驗這個是在大陸做的
He did it for ten years
他做的十年的時間
2001 to 2011
2001年到2011年
Then he went to see the toothworm's natural enemy
然後他去看牙蟲的天敵
So his natural enemy is the zerg
所以他的天敵就是異蟲
What kind of whore, grass spirit?
像什麼嫖蟲啊草靈啊
Then this spider waits
然後這個蜘蛛等等
What about the red line?
那這個紅色的線呢
The blue line is Gm has produced Bt
藍色的線是Gm有產生Bt
Bt is the protein that fights insects
Bt就是那個抗蟲的蛋白
This blue thread is Bt cotton
這個藍色的線是Bt的棉花
The red is non-Bt cotton
那紅色呢是非Bt的棉花
You can look at the trees of its predators
你可以看它天敵的樹木
in different years
在不同的年
its to overlap
它的到重疊
The curves all overlap
這個曲線都重疊
So the trees that say it's intentional insects are the same
所以表示說它的有意昆蟲的樹木是一樣的
But this green one is the cotton of Bt Aircraft Flame
可是這一條綠色的呢是Bt飛機焰的棉花
It's going to spray this sand bug spray
它去噴這個沙蟲劑
so this blue this is no sandblast
所以這個藍色的這是沒有噴沙蟲劑
But but you don't have sand spray
可是但你沒有噴沙蟲劑
It's cotton is probably also harvested
它這個棉花大概也沒收成了
Because the insects probably ate it up
因為昆蟲大概已經就把它吃得差不多了
But the machine flame is that it can resist insects
可是機焰的它是它可以抗蟲
it doesn't need to be sprayed
它不用噴藥
Then it farmers can also have a harvest
然後它農民也可以有收成
But if the plane is in flames, you go spray sand insecticide
可是飛機焰的你去噴沙蟲劑
Although sandworms can
雖然可以沙蟲
But you can see the trees of its intentional insects are greatly reduced
可是你可以看它的有意的昆蟲的樹木大為減少
The number of crab worms and tooth worms
那蟹蟲這個牙蟲的數目
You can see this non-myositic cotton
你可以看到這個非肌炎的這個棉花
hacking insecticide
砍殺蟲劑
It has so many toothworms
它的這個牙蟲的數目多那麼多
And this BT cotton or non-BT cotton
而這個BT的棉花或是非BT的棉花
It's not sprayed
它這個沒有噴藥的
Its number of toothworms is very small
它的這個牙蟲的數目是很小的
so that means
所以這意思說
It reduces the number of intentional insects
它的有意的昆蟲的數目減少
But crab worms increase
可是蟹蟲增加
In this non-BT this cotton
在這種非BT的這個棉花
in the case of pesticides
砍殺蟲劑的情況下
so it's not just cotton
所以這不只是棉花
It's drizzled with some corn peanuts soy and all
它淋進了一些玉米花生大豆等等
both also benefit
都也受益
Because of the many toothworms it's
因為很多的牙蟲它的
its this
它的這個
Ancestor worship is very wide
祭祖很廣
it likes to eat many different crops
它喜歡吃很多不同的作物
So it drenches some
所以呢它淋進了一些的
That other crops also benefit
那個其他的作物也受益
So this was published last year on
所以這個是在去年發表在
An article in Nature
Nature的一篇文章
good
好
This we mentioned the crop of these experiences
這個我們提到說這些經驗的作物
To be honest, it doesn't seem to have any impact on the environment.
說真的對於環境看起來是沒有什麼影響的
ok , then we will mention this again
好,那我們再來就要提到這個
The issue we are concerned with is that
我們關心的這個議題就是說
The Gauge Challenges We Are Facing Now
我們現所面臨的監具挑戰
is how to produce enough food
就是如何產生足夠的糧食
Come to remit a population of 9 billion
來匯保九十億的人口
this was just mentioned
這個剛剛提過
The population is now increasing at a rate that is rocketing upwards
人口現在增加的速度像火箭一樣往上衝
The various activities of our human beings
那我們的人類的各種各樣活動
for standard of living
為了徵求生活水準
Then use the car
然後用的開車子
Then this uses a lot of machinery
然後這個用了很多的機械的
wait a lot of carbon dioxide
等等產生了很多二氧化碳
So it's this warming
所以它的這個暖化
Also this keeps increasing
也這個不斷的增加
How can we do this without damaging the environment
那我們如何能夠在不破壞環境的情況下
It can also remit the global population
又可以匯保全球的人口
it's a big challenge
這是很大的挑戰
can we not use robotic hands
我們可不可以不要用機器手格
use people to follow
都用人去跟作
It seems very difficult, labor is very expensive now
好像很難喔,現在人工都很貴
Our oil is also expensive
我們油也很貴
Harvest now with this machine
現在用這個機器採收
Then carbon dioxide was produced
然後又製造了化碳
is that possible
那可不可以
no pesticides
不撒農藥
Because pesticides are not good for the environment
因為農藥做環境既然不好
that won't work
那不行
You can't harvest this
這個你又沒有辦法收成
but the man in the organic suit
但有機衣的人
This guy who promotes organic food
這個推廣有機食物的人
He said yes, we can produce
他說可以啊 我們可以生產啊
We just don't use pesticides
我們就是不用農藥
But the problem is that the cost is very high
可是問題它成本就非常高
Why
為什麼
Because you have to use a lot of labor
因為你要用很多的人工
to catch bugs
去抓蟲
to prevent
去防治
that's hard to mass produce
那又很難大量生產
its cost is high
它的成本就是高
So this environment does not destroy
所以這個環境又不破壞
It is a dilemma to increase food
又要增加糧食是兩難
is a big challenge
是很大的挑戰
Then what's another question
那再加上一個什麼問題
global land crisis
全球的土地危機
Because our arable land area is actually getting smaller and smaller
因為我們的耕地面積實際上是越來越少了
because of industrial development
因為工業的開發
There are many chemical pollution
還有很多化學的污染
Industry brings a lot of chemicals
工業就帶來很多的化學物質嘛
abnormal weather, floods, sweat disasters, etc.
氣候異常 水災 汗災等等
Then you can see that there are actually many land
然後你可以看其實有很多的地
Constantly researching why
不斷地在研化為什麼
Because we use a lot of fertilizer
因為我們用了很多的肥料
Many fertilizers are useless
很多的肥料都沒有用
no plant no absorption
沒有植物沒有吸收
Then all combined on this soil
然後都結合在這個土壤上面
Then you have no water and no water
然後你又沒有水又缺水
Originally, the water could wash away a lot of fertilizers.
本來水還可以把很多的肥料又沖走
but it lacks water
可是它缺水
So all the crystals stay in the soil
所以都結晶都留在這個土壤裡面
In the case of serious research
這研化嚴重的情況下
This plant can't grow anymore
這個植物都長不起來了
You can see you are crying to death
你看都哭死了
Then desertification is the consequence of water shortage
然後沙漠化這是缺水的後果
Many countries have this problem
現在很多國家都有這個問題
Mainland This is the northern part of mainland China
大陸這是中國大陸的北方
it lacks water and then deserts
它缺水然後沙漠化
so they're going to plant grass
所以他們要去種草
plant it with grass
草把它種上去
hope to reduce this one
希望能夠減少這一個
were able
能夠
But there is a big problem, the sand leopard
但有一個很大問題就是那個沙塵豹
Every year the dust leopard
它每年這個沙塵豹
It is because of the problem of desertification
就是因為它沙漠化的這個問題
This population has increased
這個人口增加了
We already want to increase production and increase food production
我們已經要增產增加糧食的生產
Land can be heavier and less and less
土地能夠更重又越來越少
what to do
那怎麼辦
When it comes to food, we must mention rice
提到糧食我們一定要提到水稻
Because rice is in all kinds of grains
因為水稻在各種糧食裡面
inside the main food
主要糧食裡面
It is 50% of the world's population
它是全球百分之五十的人口的
a staple food
一個主要的糧食
Corn is the highest in terms of yield
在產量上面玉米是最高的
This is corn that is usually fed to our raw vinegar
這個是玉米通常是去餵我們的生醋
Cows, pigs, sheep, etc.
牛豬、羊那一類的
So the real people eat mainly rice and wheat
所以真正人吃的主要就是稻米跟小麥
Rice is the most important grain
稻米是最主要的這樣子的糧食
ok so what
好,所以呢
Since so many people eat rice
這個既然那麼多人吃稻米
If you can increase the rice production
如果你能夠增加稻米的產量的話
The importance of its impact like this
那這樣子的它的影響的重要性
It can be shown
更是可以顯現出來
The global food
那全球的這個糧食
Because every country actually has a safety stock
因為每個國家其實都會有一個安全存量
There will be anything from three months to six months
都是會有什麼三個月到六個月
Or more than half a year, one or two years
或是半年以上一兩年都有
Different countries have different ways of doing this
不同的國家它有不同的這個作法
But let's look at the wheat, jade and soybeans
可是我們看看這個小麥跟玉跟大豆
The period from 1975 to this 2016
從1975到這個2016這一段的時間
Of course it's not that time yet
當然現在還沒到那個時候
It's about 2005 now
現在大概就是2005這一段時間
Its statistics are up to that time
它這個統計是到那段時間
You can see it this safety stock
可以看到它這個安全存量
These three very important crops
這三種很重要的這個作物
Because wheat is originally eaten
因為小麥是原吃的
This jade is eaten by animals
它這個玉是動物吃的
Soybeans are eaten by both humans and animals
大豆也是人跟動物都吃的
Its safety stock has actually been at its lowest point all the time.
它的安全存量其實一直都在降到最低點
And it's jade mushroom
而且它玉菇呢
Jade mushroom will still be very low
玉菇還是會很低
what about the rice
那稻米呢
In several major rice producing countries
在幾個主要的產稻米的國家
Like China, India and other countries
像中國、印度還有其他國家
Many countries in Southeast Asia
東南亞很多的國家
its safe food
它的安全的存糧
By 2007, this statistic had dropped to a very low level.
到這個統計是2007年已經降到很低
In fact, it is still decreasing and not increasing
其實實際上還在降低並沒有提高
so what about this problem
所以這個問題怎麼辦
If some catastrophes suddenly come
如果說突然來一些大災難
you can't produce enough food
你沒有辦法生產足夠糧食
You don't have enough food
你的存糧又不夠
like deposits in our bank
就像我們銀行的存款
If you save less than you use
你存進去的比你用的還少的話
Your bank balance will be gone in no time.
你銀行的存款一下子就沒有了
OK
OK
what else is there
那還有其他什麼問題呢
the price of oil
這個石油的價格
on the rise
在上升
What about the fertilizer?
那肥料呢
The most important thing is egg fertilizer like urea
最主要是像尿素這一類的蛋肥
Because heavy crops must use a lot of egg fertilizer
因為重作物一定要用很多的蛋肥
that egg fat
那蛋肥
it consumes a lot of energy
它非常耗能源
So when the price of oil goes up
所以石油一漲價
The price of urea will follow
尿素就跟著漲價
So can see it this price increase
所以可以看到它這個價格上升
Then the price of this rice
然後這一個稻米的價格
Of course it also rises
當然也跟著上升
because you're going to use fertilizer again
因為你又要用肥料
So farming needs oil
那耕種又要用油
so what about this question
所以這個問題呢
In fact, there is no good solution
其實也沒有什麼太好的解決的辦法
Besides these problems
那除了這些問題之外
It's even worse if you add natural disasters
再加上天災那就更糟糕了
Look at this Thailand in 2011
你看這個泰國在2011年
we probably still have the impression
我們大概可能還有印象
Its whole country was flooded with a set of lake soil
它那個全國淹水淹了一套湖土
This is the point to come to this satellite
這是點來這衛星土
it this country
它這個國家
then flooded
然後淹水呢
flooded this wide range
淹的這個範圍之廣
Then you see even this aircraft factory is flooded
然後你看連這個飛機廠都淹水了
so what year
所以那一年呢
this is 2011
這是2011年
You can look at the international food prices
你可以看國際的這個糧價
From this January to December
從這個1月開始到12月
You can see that the price of food has risen
你可以看這個糧價就上升了
Of course later
當然後來呢
sometimes there is a follow up
有時候會有後續
There will be food produced again
會有糧食又生產出來
But what?
可是呢
can clearly see
可以很明顯的看到
As long as there is such a natural disaster
只要有這樣子的天災
It is the main food production
它又是主要糧食生產過
The price of its food will definitely rise
它的糧食的價格就一定會上漲
It's not just Thailand
那不只是泰國啊
something like this is happening
都在發生類似的事情
America in 2008
美國在2008年
Major flooding in Midwest cornfields
中西部玉米田大水災
this is its cornfield
這是它的玉米田
You can't see the smoke from the corn
這個煙到玉米都看不到的
This is the system it irrigates
這是它灌溉的系統
Of course this would cause a great loss
這個當然就造成很大的損失
same place
同樣的地方
Last year it was sweat disaster
在去年卻是大汗災
severe sweating
嚴重的汗災
large flakes of corn wheat
一大片一大片的玉米小麥
The soybeans are all dried out like this
大豆都這樣子乾死了
so the same place
所以同樣的地方
can have such an extreme climate
可以有這樣子極端的氣候
to have a problem like this
來發生這樣子的問題
The entire country of the United States at that time last year
美國整個國家在去年那一年的時間
sweaty place
有汗災的地方
the darker it is
它這個顏色越深的地方
That is, the more it dries up, the more serious it is.
就是它乾汗的程度越嚴重
its serious
它嚴重的地方
almost in its crop yield
幾乎就是在它的農作物產量
highest area
最高的地區
in this generation
在這一代
what was the consequence of that
那造成的後果是怎樣
can be seen
可以看到
last year
去年啊
Many newspapers often write
這個很多的報紙常常就在寫
The price of corn has gone up
這個玉米價格黃漲啊
Then you can see what soybeans
然後可以看到什麼黃豆
up what 30
漲什麼30
Will want 39% corn 52% wheat 37%
會要39%玉米52%小麥37%
Gold Treasury 9%
黃金財長9%
Then oil 16% and so on
然後石油16%啊等等
It's just been rising. Everyone is very concerned about this issue.
就是一直在漲大家都很關心這個問題
Everyone goes out to eat, especially the students, it's very pitiful. I don't have much money.
大家到外面去吃飯尤其是學生很可憐啊本來已經沒多少錢了
Eating out is getting more and more expensive
這個出去吃飯越來越貴
I experimented with cadavers eating this a few weeks ago
我幾個禮拜前其實驗屍人吃這個
Pizza huh
Pizza huh
I haven't invited them for a long time
我已經很久沒請他們吃了
so i asked my assistant and i said
所以我就問我的助理我說
I buy all of these big Songda
這個我都買大鬆大
say how much
說多少錢
He said more than 700 yuan, I said
他說700多塊我說啊
I thought it was still more than 400 yuan
我還以為還在400多塊
I'm sorry I haven't invited them to eat for a long time
已經很抱歉很久沒請他們吃了
But it's really long
可是真的是長了很多
You can see that not only the United States but also Australia
這個你看不只美國連澳洲
Australia is already suffering from frequent droughts
澳洲呢它是已經經常性的在旱災
Australia actually produces a lot of wheat and barley
澳洲其實它生產很多小麥跟大麥
is a very important granary
是很重要的一個糧倉
It is also suffering from this drought now
它現在也是深受這個旱災所苦
Worse is predicted by 2050
更糟糕的是預測到2050年
We all like to use 2050 as an indicator now
我們現在都喜歡用2050年幫一個指標
How much does the population increase
人口增加多少
will increase from the current 7 billion to 9 billion
會從現在的70億增加到90億
more than 9 billion
超過90億
But you can see where it's dry
可是你可以看它乾旱的地方
This is also the darker the color, the more severe the drought
這個是它也是顏色越深乾旱越嚴重
Many countries will have this drought
很多的國家都會有這個乾旱的
look at this america
你看這個美國
and this south america
還有這個南美
Africa
非洲
Europe
歐洲
Asia
亞洲
the problem of drought
這個乾旱的問題
is seriously global
是很嚴重的全球性的
Then we also have problems in Taiwan
那我們臺灣也是有問題
Although we in Taiwan seem to be more redundant
雖然我們臺灣好像比較多餘
Even on the street, there are often some problems
就是街上也常常會碰到一些問題
The most important thing is what problems are happening to us now
那最主要是我們現在發生一些什麼問題
I'm sorry, how do I focus by myself?
對不起 怎麼自己對焦
OK Rice Cut Production
OK 稻米剪產
You can see our root pruning from 1981 on this
你可以看到我們的這個從1981年開始修根
So our rice crops are up to
所以我們稻米的剪產到
This is the statistics until 2009
這是統計到2009年
its cut
它的剪產
cut a lot
剪產非常的多
more than two and a half times
超到兩倍半
What about self-cultivation of food?
那糧食自主育呢
just follow up
就真的就跟著下講
Now the current food self-reliance is 32%
現在目前的糧食自主育是32%
it means
這意思是說
Our own Taiwan is very suitable for rice production
我們自己臺灣是很適合生產稻米的
we produce now
我們現在生產
To be able to produce the mother-in-law to rely on rice
能夠生產養婆自己靠稻米
It's probably just like this now
現在大概就是只有差不多這樣子
about 30%
30%左右
what is the other 70%
其他的70%是什麼
It's imported
就是進口的了
imported corn wheat
進口的玉米 小麥
soybeans
大豆啊
It has a lot of pesticides and fertilizers
它有很多的農藥 肥料
and oil
還有油
that kind
那一類
It all depends on foreign countries
都是要靠國外的
Then our own food production is so little
然後我們自己的糧食的生產那麼少
Then there are many small farmers in Taiwan
然後台灣又多小農
you see most of this
你看這個大部分 絕大部分
In fact, more than two-thirds
其實三分之二以上
All this one-hectare smallholders
都是這個一公頃的小農
cost increases
成本就增加
Plus we have a lot of this
再加上我們有很多這個
There are a lot of this luxurious farmhouse in this field
這個田裡面很多這個豪華農舍
luxury farmers
豪華農
Go to Nikan, Yilan after Chinese New Year
過完年以後去宜蘭尼堪
I really saw a lot of what is called a house
真的看到很多什麼叫做種豪舍
Plant them in a kennel from the start
種他們一開始就種狗舍
A lot of this, a small room, a small room in the field
很多這個一小間一小間在田裡面
It's really a serious problem
真的是這個問題很嚴重
let's go to that america
我們到那個美國去
not just America you don't look at America
不只是美國 你不要看美國
america is too big
美國太大了
then we go to what
然後我們去到什麼
France United Kingdom Some countries
法國 英國 一些國家
Japanese Korean family
日本 韓國人家種
The place where it is made is a kind of kennel
做的地方就是種狗舍
there are no pounds in it
裡面沒有什麼磅子
People live together in a village
人都是集中住在一個村落裡面
Only Taiwan is really a house with this
只有台灣真的是房子跟這個
smashed together first
先砸在一起的
Is it for the high-speed rail or the Taiwan Railway?
是做高鐵或是做這個台鐵
You can see such problems
都可以看到這樣的問題
So this will increase its production cost
所以這樣子都增加它的這個生產的成本
OK, let's talk again.
OK 好 那我們再來談一下說
We are now targeting this grain
我們現在針對這個糧食
What kind of goals do we have
我們有什麼樣子的遇種的目標
Although there are many problems, we still have to do
雖然問題重重我們還是要做
first very important
第一個很重要的
Increase production
提高產量
Right, we said the population is increasing so fast
對不對 我們說人口增加那麼快
Yield is really the number one priority
產量真的是第一要堅
we can take a look
我們可以看一下
This global statistic
這一個全球的統計
From 74 to 2009
從74年到2009年
Around the time of the Green Revolution
差不多就是綠色革命那段時間
Corn, Rice, Wheat, Rapeseed
玉米、稻米、小麥、油菜
Both increased by 1.5 to 2.0%
都增加1.5到2.0%
that's all
以上
So PETA has increased a lot during this period of time
所以PETA好這一段的時間增加很多
But what?
可是呢
Many other things are also increasing in price
其他的很多東西也在漲價
This is American corn
這個是以美國的玉米
Take this corn from IOWA as an example
IOWA的這個玉米為例子
corn it increased by 1.6 times
玉米它增加了1.6倍
But what?
可是呢
These cost three times the machinery
這些成本機械三倍
Four times the seed pesticide fertilizer
種子農藥肥料四倍
artificial quadruple
人工四倍
land seven times in three years
土地三年七倍
Add up all kinds
加 種種加起來
It costs ten times as much to produce as it produces
它的生產的成本是產量的十倍
Therefore, although production increases
所以雖然產量增加
But we're raising prices on everything
可是我們什麼東西都在漲價
So everyone needs enough food besides now
所以大家除了現在要有足夠的糧食
Have enough money to buy food
還要有足夠的錢買糧食
So this is a double question
所以這個是一個雙重的問題
That
那
Although it is said that in 2020
雖然說在到二零年
In 2000, our entire period from 1960 to 2020
二零零年我們整個1960年到二零年
Double our production
我們的產量加倍
But as you can see in the recent
可是你可以看到在最近的這個
In the past 20 years, his growth rate has actually slowed down.
來20年其實他的增加的速度有減緩
This is reflected in India, Asia, China
這是在印度、亞洲、中國產生倒影
His growth rate has actually slowed down.
他的增加的速度其實已經緩和下來的
There is no way to go as fast as before
沒有辦法再向過去那麼快速
So to increase the yield of this crop
所以要增加這個作物的產量
what are we going to do
我們要做些什麼事情
For a reflection
對一個以倒影為例
it has to grow well
它要長得好
It has two very important conditions
它有兩個很重要的條件
one is environmental factors
一個是環境因素
like sunshine, rain
像陽光、雨水
Another is the genetic factor
還有一個是遺傳因子
Environmental factors are
環境因子就是
no drought
不要有乾旱
Not too much salt, accumulation, low temperature, high temperature
不要太多鹽、累積、低溫、高溫
no floods etc.
不要有水災等等
another biological way
另外一個生物性的方式
It means serious illness, current weight, etc.
就是病重害、現重等等
These have to be prevented
這些都要去預防
additional genetic factors
另外遺傳的因子
that is how to make it
就是說讓它怎麼樣子
Its shape is the best
它的型態是長得最好的
Photosynthesis is the most efficient
光合的作用效率是最高的
The amount of encouragement it rises is the largest and the heaviest
它漲的鼓勵量是最多的最重的
and its roots
然後它的根呢
It can also absorb water and nutrients
也是能夠吸收水分、養分
the effect is the best
效果是最好的
Wait, there are very, very many of these conditions
等等有非常非常多的這個條件
work together to be able
配合在一起才能夠
There is a most perfect one rice
有一個最完美的一個水稻
give you the best yield
給你最好的產量
right
對不對
not so easy
不是那麼容易
but now this
可是現在這個
We who did this rice research
我們做這個水稻研究的人
have been working hard
都一直在努力
I hope you can
希望說大家可以
Explore this issue from different angles
從不同的角度來探討這個問題
Finally these good features
最後把這些好的特性
They are all concentrated in this registration.
都集中到這個報名裡面
that probably
那大概
methods of genetic engineering
基因工程的方法
It may be a more important method
可能還是一個比較重要的一個方法
because in a short time
因為在要在很短的時間內
to achieve that
要達到那個目的
In addition to production
那除了產量之外
There is another very important thing to improve
還有一個很重要的要去改良的
Just look at the drought
就是看乾旱
i just mentioned
我剛才提到
This drought is actually a serious problem
這個乾旱其實是一個很嚴重的問題
because of you
因為你
Very sick you always still have pesticides
病重悍你總是還是有農藥
But you have no rain
可是你肝悍沒有雨水
no water is no water
沒水就是沒水
It is difficult to prevent
是很難去防治的
It won't be easy unless I disturb artificial rain tomorrow
除非我明天打擾人造雨也不容易
So this tough question
所以這個肝悍的問題
It is very important for our breeding to solve
是我們育種上面很重要要解決的
that crop
那這個農作物
There is a big problem is
有一個很大問題是
it really has a lot of water
它真的有很多的水
daily food for each of us
我們每個人每天糧食
The food needed needs 3,000 liters, etc.
所需要的糧食需要三千公升等
Waiting for three tons of water to plant us every day
等三噸的水來種我們每天
the grain needed
所需要的這個糧食
You can see 70 percent of the world's fresh water
你可以看全球百分之七十的淡水
used on crops
是用在農作物上面
that this one
那這一個
Sorry, could it be pesticides?
對不起 會不是農藥
is agriculture
是農業
Most praised on agriculture
農業上面用讚最多
Then industrial household water
然後工業家庭用水
So agricultural production really uses a lot of water
所以農業生產是真的用非常多的水
Let's be brave and don't let it
我們肝悍也不要讓它
use so much water
要用這麼多的水
What about planting rice like this?
那尤其是像這個種這個水稻呢
An average kilogram of rice
平均一公斤的水稻
It also uses 2.5 tons
它也要用到 2.5 吨
2500 liters of this water
就是 2500 公升的這個水
the world probably
那全球有大概
nearly one-third of the water
有接近三分之一的水
It is used for rice irrigation
是用在水稻的灌溉上面
that other rice
那另外水稻
In addition to the evaporation of water from the leaves
它除了從葉片上面會水分會蒸發之外
The largest part is the surface of the water
最大的部分是水的表面
Surface water in the field
田裡面的表面的水
just evaporate
就是會蒸發
Of course some of it will seep a little below the ground.
當然有一些還是會稍微滲到地底下面
But its evaporation from the surface is a serious problem
可是它從表面蒸發是很嚴重的問題
So can we use less water to grow rice?
所以種水稻可不可以用少一點的水
Can you stop soaking in water all the time?
可不可以不要老是泡在水裡面
Of course we just mentioned that
當然我們剛剛有提到說
Yes weed control is an important reason
是防除雜草是一個重要的原因
But in fact, there are many heavier methods
可是實際上現在很多的更重方法
can actually assist in reducing this weed problem
其實可以協助來減少這個雜草的問題
The water in Taiwan is the same
那台灣的這個用水一樣
That's about three quarters of water
就是差不多四分之三的水
used in this agriculture
用在這個農業上面
But we also often have this problem of water shortage.
可是我們也經常有這個缺水的問題
Sometimes when there is a lack of water
有時候一缺水呢
like the recent south central
像最近中南部
Although it rains a lot in Taipei
雖然我們台北雨下很多
During the Chinese New Year, everyone is very happy to go to South Central
過年的時候大家到中南部很高興
The weather is very good in the south-central
中南部天氣非常好
Probably Taipei is very boring, the teacher is raining
大概台北就很悶老師下雨
But people in Taipei are actually lucky
可是台北的人其實有福氣
Because there is almost no shortage of water in Taipei
因為台北都幾乎不缺水
Our Bandit Reservoir has always been difficult
我們的匪萃水庫一直都難
However, the central and southern regions are often in this period of winter
可是中南部常常在這個冬天這一段時間
go really short of water
去真的很缺水
Because there is no typhoon
因為又沒有颱風
So if it's too severe
所以如果過度嚴重的時候
Farmers don't plant rice after spring
春天過完年農民不要種稻子
The government began to say that there is a shortage of water
政府又開始說缺水
We are going to use water in industry
我們跟水要去用在工業上面
Farmers don't farm
農民就不要種田
So this is actually a regular
所以這個其實經常性
It must happen every few years
隔幾年就一定要發生一次
Then the peasants are poor
然後農民就很可憐
often forget the state of mind
常常就忘田心態
For farmers, although the government subsidizes
對於農民來說雖然政府又補貼
hardworking farmer
可是勤奮的農民
he doesn't like watching this too much
他也不太喜歡看這個
Change this field back home
這個田就換回家
over there
在那裡
OK, except that Taiwan has such a problem
OK 那除了台灣有這樣的問題之外
Africa is also a serious problem
非洲也是一個很嚴重的問題
Africa also grows a lot of corn
非洲種玉米也種了很多
is their main food
是他們的主要糧食
But this corn is also very sensitive to dry welding
可是這個玉米也對乾焊也非常的敏感
The darker the country
這個顏色越深的國家
It means that it can have an irrigation system
是表示說它的這個能夠有灌溉系統
is more sufficient
是比較充足一點
Are these colors faded?
那這些顏色淡了呢
It is a place that lacks water
就是它是很缺水的地方
So water scarcity is a serious problem in Africa
所以在非洲缺水是嚴重的問題
by 2020
到2020年
predicted to be more serious
預測會更嚴重
and may
而且可能會
Corn production will be reduced by 50%
玉米會減產50%
what to do
這怎麼辦
Its population growth is also one of the fastest in the region
它的人口增加也是最快的地區之一
outside of asia
除了亞洲之外
Then cut it in half
然後還要減產一半
OK, except what we just said
OK 那除了我們剛剛講的
The purpose of forecasting is to increase production
預測的目的除了增加產量
and sweat resistant
然後耐汗之外
In fact, we also hope to improve crops
其實這個我們也希望說改進作物
Can you make this food more nutritious?
可不可以讓這個糧食比較營養一點
can be good for our health
可以對我們的健康有利
So this in our research
所以這個在我們的研究裡面
Or many people have done a lot in other research
或是很多人其他研究裡面也做很多
Then let's take an example
那我們舉例
Our genetic engineering is to increase the nutrition of food
我們基因工程在增加糧食的營養上面
what can be done
可以做什麼事
That's beta carotene
那這個是貝塔胡蘿蔔素
that is to say let this one
就是說讓這一個
Hope to be able to predict that crop?
希望能夠預出那個作物呢
It contains beta carotene
它含有貝塔胡蘿蔔素
because most crops
因為大部分的作物
Amount of Beta Carotene Contained
含有的貝塔胡蘿蔔素的量
Too much is not enough
都過滴是不夠的
that this is the world
那這個是全球
caused by vitamin A deficiency
因為缺維他命A所造成的
This night mango shrimp eye
這個夜芒蝦眼
Shrimp eyes are vitamin A deficiency
蝦眼是維他命A是缺乏
is a major reason
是一個主要的一個原因
The green one is fine.
那這個綠色的呢是沒有什麼問題
in this brain
在這個腦裡有出現
Can get enough vitamin A or betavenous waves
能夠得到充足的維他命A或是貝塔文波數
But these countries
可是這些國家
what about the yellow
這個黃色呢
The yellow one is already common
黃色的是已經普通了
that red one is very bad
那紅色的是非常的糟糕
so what
那所以呢
There are many countries in this
這個有很多的國家呢
Actually more or less
其實還是多多少少
will have some of this
都會有一些這個
vitamin deficiency problem
缺維他命的問題
Many pregnant women are also deficient in vitamin A
那很多孕婦也因為缺維他命A
Then this miscarriage
然後這個流產
Then the kid talks nonsense
然後小孩子瞎言啊
then many die
然後很多都死亡
so in this
所以在這個
beta carrot tree
貝塔胡蘿蔔樹其實
he is
他是在
What about the topic we want to talk about?
這一個我們要講的這一個主題呢
He put it in this rice
是他把它放到這個稻米裡面
that's because he turned golden
那因為他變成金黃色
We know that beta carrot trees are yellow
我們知道貝塔胡蘿蔔樹是黃黃的嘛
so when yellow
所以黃黃的時候
he called me golden rice
他叫我黃金米
What about the rice?
那稻子呢
Inside he has a right of this beta carrot tree
裡面他有一個這貝塔胡蘿蔔樹的一個權
meaning that if it can go through some process
意思是說如果它能夠經過一些過程
some genes exist
有一些基因存在
through a process
經過一個過程
beta carotene
它就可以產生貝塔胡蘿蔔素
But rice itself does not have these enzymes
可是稻米本身沒有這些酵素
So it has the original precursor empty
所以它空有原來的前驅物
But there is no way to convert it into beta carotene
可是沒有辦法轉成貝塔胡蘿蔔素
beta carotene
貝塔胡蘿蔔素
If we eat in the body
如果我們吃到體內以後
it can be converted into vitamin A
它就可以轉換成維他命A
So this scientist
所以這一個科學家
Humane
他們就基於人道
He hoped that the rice could be produced
他希望說能夠生產出來這個稻米
Because rice is actually the staple food of 50% of the population
因為稻米居然是50%人口的主食
Especially many people in this relatively weak or region
尤其是很多這個比較弱或地區的人
Eat rice as the staple food
更是吃稻米為主食
If you can let him eat the rice
那如果可以讓他自己吃的米
There is this vitamin beta carrot
就有這個維他命貝塔胡蘿蔔
If the plain skin is converted into beta life A
素皮轉換成貝塔命A的話
Many of the problems we just mentioned can be solved
我們剛才提到很多的問題就可以解決
So this technique was published in Science in 2000
所以這一個技術在2000年發表在Science
is a very sensational one thing
是非常轟動的一個一件事情
Because it's the first time to do this in a plant
因為是第一次在植物裡面做這個
Genetic engineering alters its metabolic pathways
基因工程改變它的代謝的途徑
Make it possible to generate this Beta Robb tree
讓它可以產生這個貝塔羅伯樹
Later this technique was also used in other vegetables
後來這個技術也用在其他的蔬菜
corn top
玉米上面
The corn used to look yellow
玉米原來看的黃黃的
Actually it's not a Beta Robin tree
其實它不是貝塔羅伯樹
So they put it in this corn too
所以他們也把它放到這個玉米裡面
Then come to predict this breed Mr.
那來預出這個品種的先生
this is the gentleman
就是這一位先生
The Ingeborg Park in Sweden
這個瑞典的英格魄魄園
that's his collaborator
那這是他的合作者
Peter Bayer
Peter Bayer
He published this report in 2000
他在2000年發表這個報告
The day I just talked about Science
剛剛講的那天Science
very sensational
很轟動
But at that time a two-year-old child
可是那時候一個兩歲的小孩子
To eat three kilograms of golden rice
要吃三公斤的黃金米
To be able to get enough Beta Robb trees
才能夠得到足夠的貝塔羅伯樹
So this environmental protection group keeps canceling him.
所以呢這個環保團體就不斷的取消他了
So it's useless to you
所以這你一點用都沒有嘛
How is it possible that a child only weighs three kilograms a day
怎麼可能一個小孩子一天才有三公斤
that's all eaten up
那都吃垮了
Can't get enough of this beta robin tree
還沒有得到足夠的這個貝塔羅伯樹
so wait he waited 10 years
所以等等等他等到10年
Around 2001 he retired
2001年左右的時候他退休了
Golden Girl still has no way to promote
黃金女還是沒有辦法推廣
But in the process he kept improving
可是在這個中間他不斷的改進
In 2005
2005年的時候
72 grams children eat 72 grams per day
72克小孩子每天吃72克
Just a small handful and a small bowl
只要一小把的女一小碗
will be able to get enough of the golden girl
就能夠得到足夠的黃金女
He's retired
他退休了
Now only his collaborator Peter Bayer
現在只好他的合作者 Peter Bayer
continue his efforts
繼續他做這個努力
In this Philippine International Year of Rice is the center
在這個菲律賓國際稻年就中心了
They are now constantly promoting this technology
他們現在不斷的在推廣這個技術
Because different regions of the world
因為全世界上不同的地區
Different countries
不同的國家
The rice varieties he grows are different
他種的稻年品種是不一樣的
So he wants to put this gene on different breeds
所以他要把這個基因就放到不同的品種上面
So in the future, different countries can grow
所以將來可以讓不同的國家去種
I have always hoped that it can be commercialized as soon as possible.
也一直希望說能夠趕快商業化
Because it is really possible every year
因為真的是每年可以就
very, very much of this life
非常非常多的這個生命
But environmental groups continue to protest
可是環保團體不斷的抗議
What about the research and development of this golden rice?
它這個黃金米的研發呢
Probably only cost about two million dollars
大概只花了差不多兩百萬美金
But in order to cope with environmental groups doing biosafety assessments
可是為了應付環保團體做生物安全評估
$20 million spent
花了兩千萬的美金
There is still no way to promote
還是沒有辦法能夠推廣
Many people are impatient
那很多人就不耐煩了
so this one this one is the most recent
所以這一個呢這個是最近
Sorry I forgot to call this
對不起 我忘了把它這個
Where did it come from?
從哪出處是哪裡
This is Nature
這是 Nature
An article published by Nature
Nature發表的一篇文章
it's talking about this
它就在講這件事情
Chinese children's golden rice experiment
中國小孩黃金米實驗
and then punished
然後呢被處罰
This is why some scientists were punished
這個所以就是有科學家被處罰
This is a one in Boston
這個是一個在Boston的一位
Cup University of Boston, USA
美國Boston的Cup University的
Tang Guanwen, a female professor of Chinese descent
一位華裔的女教授湯官文
Then she and Xinjiang
然後呢她跟新疆
Collaboration with some scholars in Xinjiang, Mainland China
中國大陸新疆的一些學者合作
Come
來
Eat this gold and silver for little ones
為小孩子吃這個黃金銀
Then I read his articles here
那我看他這裡面的文章
The two sides are talking about each other
雙方是各說各話
the scientists he said
那這些科學家他說
He also passed through many units
他也經過很多的單位
I agreed to do this experiment.
同意才去做這個實驗的
But after this matter was exposed by the media
可是這個事情被媒體揭發之後
Many people are afraid
很多人就怕事
then start by saying
然後開始就說
We were originally publishing the report
我們是原來是在發表報告上面
the people who hang on to you start saying
掛您的那些人就開始說
We also don't know what experiments he was doing.
我們也不知道他在做些什麼實驗
then i have nothing to do with me
然後我跟我無關什麼
Because in the end someone was arrested and locked up
因為最後還是有人被抓去關了
so it's a pity
所以是很可惜
Then he drew this cartoon
然後他畫的這個漫畫
like an american
就好像是美國人
because you see he has an american flag on his tie
因為你看他領帶上面有美國國旗
Then he put this gold and silver this gold and silver
然後他就把這個金銀這個黃金銀
for the children of China
就為中國的小孩子
So in fact his report
所以其實他這一篇報告
published has been published
發表的已經發表了
And his result is very good
然後他的這個結果成效非常好
Because they had three sets of experiments
因為他們當初有三組實驗
A group is to eat gold
一組是吃黃金
One group is to eat spinach
一組是吃菠菜
Another group is to eat
另外一組是吃
Beta Carotene Capsules
貝塔胡蘿蔔素的膠囊
The results of it
結果呢
Eating gold gives you exactly the same effect as taking beta carotene capsules
吃黃金你跟吃貝塔胡蘿蔔素的膠囊的效果完全一樣
So it actually works really well
所以實際上效果是很好
But because of the media
可是因為媒體
Then the protests of environmental groups
然後環保團體的抗議
Now temporarily suppressed again
現在暫時又被壓下來了
But the mainland
可是大陸
He's genetically engineered various crops
他是做基因工程的各種各樣的作物
A very positive country
推的非常的積極的一個國家
All but the most active countries in the world
全世界上除了最積極的國家
The United States is of course very active
美國當然是很積極
or countries in the Americas
或是美洲的國家
Because they make a lot of money by exporting this gene
因為他們靠這個基因的外銷實在是賺非常多的錢
The other one is like China, India
另外一個就像中國、印度
because he has too many people
因為他人口太多了
He is very sensitive to the food of the people
他對人民的糧食非常的敏感
Our government in Taiwan is not sensitive at all
我們台灣的政府一點都不敏感了
we must be
我們一定要是
Autonomy is only 32%
自主力才32%
Do you know what percentage is in mainland China?
你知道中國大陸幾%嗎?
it's 95%
它95%
So mainland China pays more attention to whether its people can have enough to eat
所以中國大陸更重視它人民能不能吃得飽
You can't have enough to eat, you can't eat enough
你也吃不飽 你也食為天
If you can't eat enough, you will be messed up
吃不飽就亂了
So the top executives in the mainland said
所以它大陸的高層說
Although this happened
雖然發生這件事情
Our genetic engineering technology is still the same
我們的基因工程技術還是照樣規
Because they see the future really depends on this technology
因為它們看到未來真的是非靠這個技術不可
So in addition to the golden rice just mentioned
所以除了剛剛講的黃金米之外
In fact, there are many other things to do
其實還有很多其他的事要做
many people are doing
也很多人在做
increase its protein content
增加它的蛋白質含量
Iron core, anti-oxidant, etc.
鐵 芯 抗氧晃物等等
Actually m it is very
其實米它是非常
Its protein quality is very good
它的蛋白質品質非常好
easy to digest
很容易消化
Too bad it's not high enough
可惜它的含量不夠高
So many people say
所以也很多人說
can hope to increase its protein content
能夠希望增加它的蛋白質的含量
These genetically engineered plants
這些基因工程的這個植物
what else can be done
還可以做些什麼事
Let's take an example
我們舉一個例子
it can produce this oral vaccine
它可以生產這個口服疫苗
That is to say, you are produced in the tomato
就是說你生產在番茄裡面
produced in spinach
生產在菠菜裡面
You just dry the capsules and put them on
你只要乾燥膠囊裝上去
Then the doctor will tell you
然後醫生就告訴你說
you eat two this week
你這個禮拜吃兩顆
next week two
下禮拜兩顆
Eat a few in a few weeks
再過幾個禮拜吃幾顆
you are vaccinated
你就接種了
For many countries in this weak or region
對很多這個弱或地區的國家
is very important
是非常的重要
Because many vaccines need to be iced
因為很多的疫苗要冰
They don't have a fridge, they don't have mats
他們沒有冰箱 沒有墊
or no medical staff
或是說沒有醫護人員
Can help them inoculate these diseases
可以幫他們做這些病棋的接種
So this oral vaccine
所以這個口服疫苗
actually very good
其實是非常好的
i think kids
我想小孩子呢
not only children
不只小孩子
Many adults are afraid of needles
很多大人都怕打針
so in the future
所以以後呢
this oral vaccine
這一個口服疫苗
You just eat it and get vaccinated.
你就吃進去就可以接種了
This is a lot of successful examples
這個是很多成功的例子
has been very successful
已經非常成功
And some of them are already commercialized
而且是已經有一些開始在商業化了
so this
所以這個
It was drawn by my daughter
當初是我女兒畫的
Then he draws his brother
那他畫他弟弟
well , this time he drew his dad
好,這次他畫他爸爸
Head of education teacher
教育長老師
that because we all know
那個因為我們都知道
It's just that people don't like injections.
就是就是打針大家都不喜歡嘛
But this future oral vaccine
可是這一個將來的這個口服疫苗
is really able to do this
真的是能夠做到這一點
ok , ok , let ' s talk again
OK,好,那我們再來談一下
What kind of work are we doing in Taiwan
我們在台灣在做一些什麼工作
We are doing the function letter gold of the plant
我們在做植物的功能信金
Somatic research, it should be said that the functional information of rice
體研究,應該是說水稻的功能信金
body research
體研究
Because we need to borrow useful genes from plants
因為我們要跟植物來借有用的基因
we just talked a lot
我們剛剛講了很多
Can do this kind of genetic engineering law
可以做這個基因工程律種
then we have to find out
那我們必須要先去找出
what kind of genes are useful
什麼樣的基因是有用的
Then let's put the usage where I want it
然後我們來把用到放到我想放的地方去
Then this is his rice
那這個是水稻他的
A schematic diagram of the 12 chromosomes
12條染色體的示意圖
He refers to the number of his genes one by one
他一條一條的是指他的基因的數目
The darker the color, the number of genes
顏色越深表的基因數目
more
越多
Then this in Japanese
那這個在日本人
when they first started
他們剛開始的時候
It is he who does the job of interpreting
是他做這個解敘的工作
What is an explanation?
什麼叫解敘啊
as if
就好像是
word in a dictionary
一本字典裡面的字
ABCD is in a mess
ABCD 排的亂七八糟的
Then what
然後呢
You're going to start arranging it in ABCD
你要開始把它排成 ABCD 排好
Then XYZ lines up
然後 XYZ 排好
So it's a job of interpretation
所以這是一個解敘的工作
So the position of each experience on the chromosome
所以把每一個經驗在染色體上面的位置
you fix it
你就把它定出來
that job is very important
那這個工作很重要
so at first
所以剛開始的時候
japanese do it themselves
日本人自己做
when he started doing
他開始做的時候
Many people laugh at him as stupid
很多人都笑他傻
Because this job costs a lot of money
因為這個工作花很多錢
it will take a lot of time
還要花很多的時間
that was later
那可是後來呢
Many countries have begun to discover
很多國家開始發現
This is a very important job
這個是很重要的一個工作
then start assisting
那就開始協助
turn around and look at him
回身一看他
have completed this chromosome
有完成這個染色體
the work of interpretation
這個解敘的工作
National conditions can be hung on it
國情就可以掛上去
good
好
So Japan hangs this much
所以日本掛這多
then other countries
然後其他國家
Then our national flag of the Republic of China
然後我們中華民國的國旗
This is us in 1999 2004
這是我們在1999年2004年
former botanical institute
之前的植物所
It is now called Plant Language Living Documentation Office
現在叫植物語維生文件所
This is a lot of teachers
這個很多老師
Including Mr. Xi Yu as the program host
包括習俞老師是計畫主持人
he is here now
他現在也在這邊
we gritted our teeth
我們那時候咬著牙
Because it costs a lot of money to do it
因為花很多錢去做這件事情
that just started
那剛開始呢
I also want to say if it's me
也有想說是不是自己
don't totally do that much
不要完全做那麼多
don't spend so much money
不要花那麼多錢
But our neighbors are not alone
可是我們的鄰居不是單單
After that, the national flag will be placed with us
那以後呢國旗要跟我們擺在一起
So we did it by ourselves
所以呢我們後來是自己完成了
so what about our flag
所以我們的國旗呢
always on the fifth chromosome
永遠在第五條染色體上面
No one can remove him
這個是誰都沒有辦法把他移走
So this is a very important job
所以這是非常重要的一個工作
Alright, let's line up from ABCD to XYZ
好那我們一本字點ABCD到XYZ排好了
But the problem is he didn't hold tight
可是問題是他沒有住緊
you don't know what it means to say book
你不知道說book是什麼意思
what does girl mean
girl是什麼意思
Then we have to give him meaning
那我們要給他意思啊
So we go down and take each
所以我們就下去把每一個
The function of the gene needs to be solved
基因的功能要把它解出來
Waterways contain nearly 40,000 genes
水道含有接近四萬個基因
How to study the functions of so many genes
這麼多個基因的功能要怎麼去研究
it's difficult
這是很困難的
Because often a person's life
因為常常一個人一輩子
Studying only one gene previously
只研究一個基因在以前
In other words, several people are studying a single gene
或是說一個基因好幾個人在研究
So we have a strategy
所以我們就一個策略
That is to say, we just use the method of genetic engineering
就是說我們就把利用基因工程的方法
Insert it from a foreign gene
從外來的基因把它插進去
Feel free to plug in and have a chance
隨意插進去就有機會
it plugs into the gene
它會插到基因上面
It will destroy the gene
它就會把這個基因就破壞了
what happens to it after it is destroyed
破壞以後它會發生什麼事情
mutation
就突變
Let's talk about mutations later
我們等一下再講突變
So here we are
所以我們就這個在
I didn't write here
我這邊沒寫
Ten years from roughly 2002 to 2012
十年的時間在差不多2002年到2012年
Doing this job for more than ten years
超過十年的時間做這個工作
Then we build this channel
然後我們建立這個水道
Gene Mutation Database and Database
基因突變總緣庫跟資料庫
In total we have more than 100,000 mutant lines
我們總共有超過10萬個突變品系
Then what gene, what DNA is inserted into our
然後我們什麼基因 什麼DNA被插進去
we all have to figure it out
我們都有去把它解出來
Make a database with more than 60,000
做一個資料庫 有超過6萬個
So we publish this report
所以我們就發表這個報告
Mr. Li and other cooperating teachers
行李老師還有其他的合作的老師
This is a very important job
這個是很重要的一個工作
Because all over the world like this
因為全世界上像這樣子的
Mutation library and database like this
這樣子的突變庫跟資料庫
also only 4
也只有4個
Taiwan, South Korea, China and France
台灣韓國 還有中國跟法國
China, of course, has many
中國當然是有很多個
Because it has a lot of people, it has to do this thing
因為它人多 它要做這件事情
it is also very easy to do
它也是很容易做的
But in terms of quality and publicity
可是在品質上面 在公開上面
On the ease of use of the database
在資料庫的容易使用度上面
Taiwan and South Korea are the two best general pools
台灣跟韓國是最好的兩個總緣庫
Then we added some special new clothes
然後我們又加上有一些特殊的新裝
I have time to explain to you
有時間跟大家做解釋
That is to say, our quality is actually quite good.
就是說我們的品質其實是相當好的
So we accumulated like this
那我們所以就累積這樣子的
Picture total circle library
圖片總圓庫
Then we published
然後我們才發表的
One year later there will be this Science
一年之後就有這個Science
sorry for the question
對不起這個問題
Cannot return the ticket directly
不能直接回票
Puncture Science
Puncture Science
He just came one day to give my aunt
他就有一天他就突然來給我的姨妹
in 2008
在2008年
I published in 2007
我2007年發表
In 2008
那2008年的時候
he just told us
他就跟我們講說
tell me
跟我講說
Our report
我們這一篇報告
In the plant field of the world
在全球的植物領域裡面
The number of times used by the camp is the top one percent
被營用的次數是前百分之一
So it's a big honor
所以是一個蠻大的光榮的
So he asked me a lot of questions
所以他就問了我很多的問題
say why
說為什麼
Your total library
你們這個總圓庫
Can be used by so many people
能夠被那麼多人來營用
I will tell them the reason
我就把這個理由也告訴他們
I said that everyone paid attention
我就說大家有重視到
Our total library
我們這個總圓庫
and why
然後也為什麼
This was just introduced by the vice president
這個剛剛副院長介紹
Our Gates Foundation
我們這個蓋茲基金會
support us to do
支持我們做
This project of a western rice in this world
這個全球的一個西貨水稻的這個計畫
Because rice is a three-type plant
因為水稻是一個西三型的植物
That's like corn sorghum
那像玉米高粱啊
Sugarcane is a four-type plant
甘蔗是西四型的植物
Its photosynthesis efficiency is better
它的光合作用效率比較好
well, we don't have time to explain this today
好,這個我們今天沒有時間解釋
But now everyone wants to say
可是呢,現在大家就希望說
Can convert rice into something like corn sorghum
能夠把水稻轉換成像玉米高粱這樣子
Its efficiency of photosynthesis is improved
它的光合作用的效率提高
In this way, its yield can be increased
這樣子的話,它的產量就可以提高
Because the photosynthetic efficiency of corn is 40% higher than that of rice
因為玉米的光合作用效率比水稻高百分之四十
He said that if the photosynthetic efficiency of rice can
他說如果水稻的光合作用效率可以
If it is increased by 140% like corn
跟玉米一樣也提高百分之十四十的話
We could probably be more than 40 percent of the population
我們可能可以多為百分之四十多出來的人口
So that's why it's important to have a global program
所以這是為什麼一個很重要的一個全球性的計畫
There are nearly 25 research laboratories around the world participating
那全球有接近二十五個研究室參加
Then Mr. Li Yu and I represent Taiwan
那我跟行李宇老師,我們代表台灣
It's in this plan
就是在這個計畫裡面
So this also shows that our
所以這個也顯示出我們這個
An importance of the general research library
總研庫的一個重要性
Okay, so what is a mutation?
那好 那這個什麼叫突變
What exactly is our general research library doing?
我們這個總研庫到底做出什麼事情
This is a diagram
這個是一個示意圖
That is to say, the nucleus inside our cells
就是說我們細胞裡面的細胞核
It contains our chromosomes
裡面就是有我們的染色體
Chromosomes have DNA
染色體上面就有 DNA
it's our genetics
這是我們的遺傳性
genetic material
遺傳物質
Then our DNA will make protein
那我們 DNA 會做蛋白質出來
what we just said
那我們剛剛講
We just insert the DNA from the outside
我們就從外界把 DNA 插進去
right to destroy the gene
對不對 去破壞基因
So it's us inserting the gene
所以就是我們插進去基因
So something like this
所以這樣的話
Your protein is also destroyed
你的蛋白質也會被破壞
Then it starts to have some traits
這樣它有一些性狀就開始出來了
Normally, there is only one flower
正常的話 只有一朵花
I am now three flowers
我現在變成三朵花
This seed was originally so small, but it has become so big
這個種子本來這麼小 變這麼大
Originally without color, it becomes colored
本來沒有顏色 變有顏色
I used to be so tall, but now I'm so short
本來這麼高 變這麼矮
I used to be so tall, I became so tall
本來這麼高 變這麼高
higher
更高
This can grow to over 200 cm in a greenhouse
這個在溫室裡面可以長到超過 200 公分
This should have gone up
這個本來應該往上漲了
It loses its direction and keeps spinning
它這個失去方向就在那裡一直轉
and this angle
還有這個角度呢
should have been upwards
本來應該是向上的
it becomes horizontal
它這個就變成橫的
the leaves swell
葉子葉片就橫漲
Then some leafy trees are gone
那有的葉粒樹就不見了
There are so many
這個等等有非常非常的多
we are a vault
我們這是一個保庫
There are a lot of such univariate traits in it.
裡面就有非常多的這樣的獨變性狀
allows us to study many gene functions
可以讓我們來研究很多的基因功能
because i know now
因為我現在就知道
what kind of genetic disruption is this one
這一個是什麼樣的基因破壞
Then let me become like this
然後讓我變成這樣子的性狀
This is a method for studying gene function
這個就是一個研究基因功能的一個方法
Then we get from our general research database
那我們從我們的總研庫裡面
just find some important genes
就找到一些重要的基因
This is the meter that controls it
這個是控制它的米
That can also be high yield
那也可以高產量
You can see the meter get bigger
你可以看到這個米變大
Broken and more
碎變多
the whole encouragement
這個整個的這個鼓勵
it also increases
它也變多
Then this is cooperating with foreign biotechnology companies
那這個跟國外的生技公司有在合作
this effect
這個效果
they work pretty well
他們做起來效果相當好
what about the other
那另外呢
We just mentioned the first green revolution
我們剛才提到第一次綠色革命
This rice and wheat make it dwarf
這個水稻跟小麥讓它變矮
right
對不對
so we are
所以我們在
But now the traditional filter
可是現在傳統濾種上面
It's not easy for you to control its height at will
你還不太容易隨意控制它的高度
The current rice is still somewhat too high
那現在的水稻還是多少稍微有點太高
If possible in such
如果能夠在這樣的
Almost 80% of the words left
差不多只剩下 80% 的話
or 70% its that height might be just right
或是 70% 它的那個高度可能是正好的
So now we can filter out varieties like this
所以呢我們現在可以濾出這樣子的品種
so any height is fine
所以什麼高度都可以
Then let's look at its output
然後呢我們就來看它的產量
Sure enough, this height
果然這個高度呢
Its output can be increased by 30%
它的產量可以增加 30%
And it is also more resistant to soldering
而且它也比較耐焊
So this is what we have now
所以呢這個是我們現在
Some research results that can be done in Taiwan
在臺灣能夠做出來的一些研究成果
And we just mentioned that
還有我們剛剛有提到說
Is this a dry soldering problem?
這個乾焊的問題對不對
we also have this gene
我們也有這個基因
What about gene transfer?
那做基因轉職呢
experience non-experience you from appearance
經驗非經驗你從外觀
Can't see it
看不太出來
But you didn't water for two weeks
可是你兩個禮拜不澆水
The leaves are curled up
葉片都捲起來了
Then you water it for another thirty minutes
那你再給它澆水三十分鐘
Only genetically engineered it can recover
只有基因工程的它能夠恢復
To genetically engineered it dies
對基因工程的它就死了
good
好
In such a dry place in the future
將來在這麼乾旱的地方
Is it possible that we can grow some rice
我們有沒有可能可以種一些稻子
good
好
This is a dream to pursue
這個由夢就去追尋
this is
這個是
This is Ang Lee, he also said
這個是李安他也是說
he has been chasing his dream
他一直在追求他的夢
Then he also succeeded
然後他也成功了
I think for those of us who do molecular biology
我想對於我們做分子生物的人
We also often have a dream
我們也常常有一個夢
It's actually based on your imagination
就是其實憑著你的想像
There are many things that are possible in the future
有很多事情將來是都是可能實現的
Then the first question is actually a lot of questions
然後第一問其實也是很多的問題
That is, in many countries, the temperature may be too low
就是很多的國家可能溫度太低
Or high dimension and high altitude or something
或是維度高海拔高什麼的
Sometimes it's cold in winter
冬天有時候寒流一來
Many crops will freeze to death
很多的作物就會冷死
Therefore, the first question is also an important issue.
所以抗第一問也是個重要的議題
We have a waterway of genetically modified genes here
我們這邊有一個基因轉值的基因的水道
This is a non-genetic diversion
這是非基因的轉水道
This one here is also a gene
這邊這一個也是基因
It's just that we genetically make it behave less
只是我們把它的基因讓它表現變少
so it won't work
所以它就不行了
It won't work after seven or eight hours on the fourth road
在四路七八個鐘頭它就不行了
Then this non-gene and this have a lot of performance
那這個非基因跟這個有大量表現
The genes we gave it were okay
我們給它的基因的還可以
That's 18 hours later
那可是18個小時之後呢
Only the water height of our genes can survive
只剩下我們基因的水高還能活下來
The non-genetic ones and the ones that we make the gene expression less will not work
非基因的跟我們讓它基因表現變少的都不行了
So this is the cold resistance gene
所以這個是抗冷的基因
so many places are too cold
所以很多地方太冷
Can we also be in those places in the future
我們將來是不是也可以在那些地方
These cold resistance genes can also be planted
也可以種這些抗冷的基因
now because it is
現在因為實在是
really urgent
實在逼急了
Many places were originally unsuitable for planting crops
很多的地方原來不適合種植作物的地方
We will all find ways to plant
我們都會想辦法去種
what about words
那以言呢
Originally also
原本也是
We have this genetically modified waterway
我們有這個基因轉值的水道
before processing
處理之前
This is
這是
Also upgrade the fly gene
也升型了飛基因的
The five next to this
這個旁邊的這五顆
All five lines were genetically transformed
五個品系都是基因轉型的
then soak in salt water
然後泡在鹽水裡面
250g minimum
250克minimum
it's very high in salt
這是非常高的鹽
salt concentration
鹽的濃度
almost like sea water
跟海水差不多
This soaked for three weeks
這個泡了三個禮拜
You see, this genetically transformed person is dead
你看這個飛基因轉型的就死了
What we genetically transform can also be peeled off
我們基因轉型的還可以剝下的
So this gene is very powerful
所以這個基因很厲害啊
our this
我們這個
This Taiwan, this southwest salt
這個台灣這個西南鹽
There are still many deserted salt pans
還有很多荒廢的鹽田
What about the future?
將來呢
Now
現在
Is it possible in the future
將來是不是有可能
These crops can also be grown
也可以去種的這些作物
good ok
好 OK
ok finally let's talk about this
好最後我們再來講一下這個
Current Global Trends in GM Crops
目前全球基改作物的趨勢
Because we've talked so much about genetics
因為我們講了那麼多基因的東西
that global
那全球
everybody every country
大家每個國家
what kind of thought is it now
現在到底是一個什麼樣的想法
what are they doing
他們在做些什麼事情
this
這個
Genetic crops started in 1996
基因的作物是1996年開始的
So this curve you can see
所以這個曲線你可以看到
by 2011
到 2011 年
His increased area
他的這個增加的面積
This is a developing country
這個是開發中國家
combined by developing countries
以開發的國家合起來的
only so much time
只有這麼多的工期
This is only 15,000 hectares
這個 15,000 公頃而已
160 million hectares by 2011
到 2011 年變成 1.6億公頃
9% of global renewable energy
全球 9% 的可更定能
Now
現在
Genetic crops
都在種基因的作物
He multiplied 10,000 times
他增加了 1 萬倍
Think about the weak things that can make the world go like this
你想想看能夠讓全球這樣子去之弱物
Many countries go to the weak
很多國家去之弱物
He must be something that can stand the test
他一定是經得起考驗一個東西嘛
Otherwise, it is impossible for so many countries
不然不可能那麼多國家
in species
在種
And what about his production value?
然後他的產值呢
is continuously rising until 2011
是不斷的一直上升到 2011 年
What about the production value of the seeds?
光是種子的產值呢
reached $12 billion
就達到 120 億美金
This is an area below
這是下面有一個面積
Then there is the production value
然後有的是產值
what crops are grown
種植的作物是什麼
The main ones are soybeans, corn, cotton and rapeseed
主要的還是最多的是大豆、玉米、棉花跟油菜
Soybeans are eaten by both animals and humans
那大豆是動物跟人都吃的
corn is eaten by animals
玉米是動物吃的
Cotton, clothes, and rapeseed are eaten by people
棉花、衣服、油菜是人吃的
Then this is the area where it is planted
那這個是它的這個種植的這個面積
One million hectares
一百萬公頃來算
Then what
然後呢
What kind of features are most
大部分是什麼樣的特性
Anti-weed killer or anti-insect or double anti-
抗殺草機或是抗蟲或是雙抗
Now there are a lot of two features together
現在有很多都是兩個特性在一起的
So insect resistance is what I just explained to you
所以抗蟲就是我剛剛有跟大家解釋
That protein of that BT
那個那個BT的那個蛋白
I didn't talk about anti-weed killers in particular today
抗殺草機我今天沒有特別講
It also has many benefits
它也有很多的好處啦
But I want to say don't say it seems to be doing publicity for these companies
可是我想說不要說好像專為這些公司在做宣傳
So I'm not talking about this in particular
所以我也沒有在特別要講這個
But it can be seen that
可是可以看到說
Its area is really rising
它的這個面積真的是一直在上升
OK, this area has just been increased
OK這個面積剛剛已經提高了
we really tuned in
我們真的調過去
Where are the countries where the planting is distributed?
那種植的國家分佈在哪裡
These colored, colored countries
這些有顏色的、上色的國家
is the country where it was planted
就是種植的國家
By 2011 there were already 29 countries
到2011年已經有29個國家
I have been teaching for so many years
我這個教書這麼多年來
Almost every year I have to update
幾乎是每年我都要更新
must update why
一定要更新為什麼
Because almost two countries are added every year
因為每年幾乎是增加兩個國家
the number of two countries
兩個國家的數目
that this
那這個
this
這個
of course you look at me
當然你看我這個
The United States, of course, is the first
美國當然是最開始
Canada
加拿大
Then this Sino-American
然後這個中美
then south american countries
然後南美的國家
Most of them are planted
絕大部分都種了
Then the mainland, India, South Africa, Australia
然後大陸、印度、南非、澳洲
you see even this europe
你看連這個歐洲
Several countries have planted
都有幾個國家都種了
Look like Sweden, Germany, Spain
你看像這邊瑞典、德國、西班牙
all kinds
都有種了
OK
OK
so you can watch a trend
所以你可以看一個趨勢
Then
然後
Well, so many countries are doing
好 那麼多國家都在做
But many people still care
可是還是很多人會關心說
This machine-modified crop is being used by our food and the environment
這個機改的作物被我們的食品和環境
Safe, I want to do it again, there are many people
安全啊 我想再做有很多人
It's probably always been the same problem.
大概也是一直有這樣子的問題
Then we are here to explain to you
那我們就是來跟大家解釋一下
let's start by saying
我們首先先說一下
Because we just had a rough idea of ​​what the machine modification is all about.
因為我們剛剛大概知道機改是怎麼回事嘛
It's like putting a gene from the outside and then putting it in.
好像把一個基因就是從外面再放進去這樣子
But let's find out first
那可是我們先來了解一下
In fact, our human body already has a lot of these
其實我們的人體裡面早就有很多這些
We just said that in the process of green seeding
我們剛剛也講說在綠種過程中
Many genes have been exchanged like this
很多的基因已經就是這樣子換來換去
That plants, animals, including people, etc.
那個植物啊 動物啊 包括人啊什麼的
That person, including people, some very important things
那人 包括人啊 有些很重要的是是什麼
Let's first look at the cells of our human body
我們先看我們的人體的細胞
Inside human cells Inside animal cells
人體的細胞裡面 動物的細胞裡面
There must be this green line
一定都有這個綠線體
But what about plants, it will have a
可是植物呢 它會有一個
It's only for plants
這是只有植物有的
neither animals
動物也沒有
this is our nucleus
這是我們的細胞核
Our genetic material is inside this nucleus
我們的遺傳物質就是在這個細胞核裡面
For plants it has this cell coin
對於植物來說它有這個細胞幣
But animals don't have this cell currency
可是動物不會有這個細胞幣
These are two very important organs
這是兩個很重要的器官
Why do I mention these two organs in particular
為什麼我要特別提這兩個器官
Leaf lift phenomenon
葉律提跟力現象
Yelu mentioned that it needs to carry out photosynthesis
葉律提它要進行光合作用
so sun down
所以太陽能下來
Then there is this carbon dioxide and water for photosynthesis
然後有這個二氧化碳跟水進行光合作用
produce glucose
產生葡萄糖
Glucose provides this force embodiment
葡萄糖提供這個力現體
to generate energy
來產生能量
So our sugar photosynthesis
所以我們的產生的糖光合作用
Yeluti
是靠葉律提
Energy is generated by this force
產生能量是靠這個力現體
All animals must have this power manifested
所有的動物一定要有這個力現體
otherwise there is no way to live
不然沒有辦法活
You can't live because you don't have energy
因為你沒有能量你活不下去
All plants must have both
所有的植物這兩個都要有
Yeluti
它要有葉律提
it has cuboid
它有立線體
That plant contributes a lot
那植物它貢獻是很大的
Before this teacher Wu Suxin
這個吳素信老師之前
I guess he also said this knowledge
這個知識想言他也講過
this inside our earth
這個我們地球裡面
all carbohydrates
所有的碳水化合物
Almost all are produced by plants for us.
幾乎都是靠植物幫我們生產出來的
what we eat every day
我們人每天吃的東西
are produced by plants
都是靠植物生產出來的
multidimensional organisms
甚至很多維生物
it depends on it
它也要靠它過
so no plants
所以沒有植物啊
The world has probably
這個世界上大概已經
Only some dimensional creatures are left
只剩下一些維生物而已
those two organs
那這兩個器官
Cells 2.7 billion years ago
在27億年前的細胞
In fact, these two organs do not exist.
其實是沒有這兩個器官的
But I don't know under what circumstances
可是不曉得在什麼樣子的情況下
this our cells
這個我們的細胞
prokaryotic it is a prokaryotic cell
原核它是原核細胞
Originally from lower organisms
原來是低等生物的
it eats into the cuboid
它吃進去這個立線體
You can see that it contains this stereo
你看就含有這個立線體了
And then there are some cells
然後之後有一些細胞呢
It's a leprosome that's actually a bacterium
它這個瀝線體實際上是一個細菌
Bacteria
細菌來的
After it eats the bacteria
它把這個細菌吃進去以後
This bacterium becomes
這個細菌就變成
In this cell it becomes a stroma
在這個細胞裡面變成一個瀝線體
Then there are some cells
然後有一些細胞呢
it eats some algae
它又吃進去一些藻類
So what happens after the algae enters?
所以這個藻類進去以後呢
become this plant
變成這個植物
it becomes leptin and chloroplast
它變成有瀝線體也有葉綠體
So plants can photosynthesize
所以植物它能夠光合作用
What about its primitive ancestor?
它的這個原始的祖先呢
from this photosynthetic bacterium
就是從這個能夠進行光合作用的細菌來的
So our current higher organisms
所以我們現在的高等生物啊
not just all kinds of animals
不只是各種各樣的動物
including humans
包括人類
And this variety of plants
還有這個各種各樣的植物
inside our cells
我們的細胞裡面
There are already some of its fire doctor creatures coming
早就已經有一些它的火醫生物來的
or genes from algae
或是藻類來的基因
already inside us
已經在我們的體內了
So after so many years of evolution
所以經過這麼多年的演化呢
can coexist with us
跟我們能夠共存
Then look at the natural world
然後呢你看自然界中呢
what about all creatures
所有的生物呢
cells themselves
細胞本身就
constantly evolving
不斷地在演化
you don't need to green it
你不需要去綠它
It's already evolving
它已經就是不斷地在演化
You see, there can be many, many butterflies
你看蝴蝶可以非常非常的多
Beetles can be very, very plentiful
甲蟲可以非常非常的多
Then what
然後呢
like this fish for example
像這個魚為例子
You are a fish and it can live well
你一隻魚它可以活得好好的
What about two fish?
兩隻魚的情況下呢
What about good friends getting married and having kids?
要嘛就是好朋友結婚生小孩
produce a better fish to survive
產生一個更好的魚活下來
then if you can't
那如果你沒有辦法
have produced better fish
有產生更好的魚
Your original fish may not be competitive
你那原來的魚可能就沒有競爭力了
this is irresponsible
這是不盡天責
It turned out to be worse
原來比較不好的
was wiped out
就被消滅了
just die
就死了
So in nature
所以自然界中呢
In fact, it is constantly
其實就是不斷地
have been genetically between various organisms
一直在基因各種生物之間
Inside the creature
生物裡面
Its genes are constantly changing
它的基因就是不斷地在做改變
Except for this natural world
那除了這種自然界
natural mating
自然交配啊
among many other reasons
很多其他原因之外
All living things are infected by viruses
所有的生物都會被病毒感染
What about the virus?
這個病毒呢
It also carries genes into our body
它也會把基因帶到我們的體內
then
然後就
Collapsing into our genetic body
塌到我們的基因體裡面
then become part of us
然後就變成我們的一部分
So actually you say that nature species
所以實際上你說自然界種
In fact, the gene is constantly mixing
實際上這個基因就是不斷的一直在混合
is a very natural phenomenon
是一個很自然的現象
OK so virus infection
OK 所以病毒感染
It is also the constant mutation and evolution of this gene
也是這個基因不斷的突變跟演化的
a very important reason
一個很重要的原因
ok then let's find out
好 那我們先了解一下
Well, this genetic change
好 這個基因改變
It's not really a terrible thing
其實不是太可怕的事情
Because nature is constantly happening
因為自然界種的不斷的在發生
But it's a real problem for us
可是對我們很現實的問題
which means we eat these plants
就是說我們吃這些植物
safe or not
安不安全
like a genetic plant before it goes to market
就像一個基因的植物在上市之前
it will definitely do some experiments
它一定會做一些實驗
Toxicity to animals Hypersensitivity
對動物的毒性 過敏性
changes in nutrients, etc.
營養成分的改變等等
It has to go through these experiments
它一定都要經過這些實驗
I always say
那我常講說
These things are genetically modified
這些東西基因改造的東西
There is nothing to be afraid of when you eat it in your stomach
吃到肚子裡面沒有什麼好害怕
Why
為什麼
Because the main components are DNA and protein
因為主要的成分就是DNA跟蛋白質
Just like the rice we eat every day
就跟我們每天吃的米呀
vegetables water
蔬菜呀 水
The ingredients are almost the same, after eating in the stomach
成分都差不多,吃到肚子裡面以後
inside your stomach
你那肚子裡面腸胃裡面
There are already a lot of this decomposing mold
就已經有一大堆的這個分解霉
Inside the Tuo Ye, Stomach Leaf, Chair Leaf, and Intestine Leaf
那拓葉啊胃葉啊椅葉啊腸葉裡面啊
Just a lot of decomposing mold
就一大堆的分解霉呢
protein
就可以把譬如說有一蛋白
There are protein molds, nucleic acid molds, etc.
有蛋白霉啊有核酸霉啊等等
digested
就消化掉了
Or the absorption of nutrients
或吸收的變養分了
So, the genetic thing it's not
所以呢,基因的東西它不是
Phytochemicals are not pesticides
素化劑不是農藥
not this preservative
不是這個防腐劑
not antibiotics
不是抗生素
Not what these you fear will cause
不是什麼這些你害怕會引起
something that accumulates or is harmful to a person
對人累積或對人有害的東西
Basically, it is digested in the stomach
基本上吃到腸胃裡面就消化掉
This experiment has done a lot
這個實驗做得非常的多
Animal experiments are done a lot
動物的實驗做得很多
there is evidence
是有證據的
So actually we really are
那實際上呢我們真的是
Already eat a lot of genetic stuff
已經就吃很多基因的東西了
Although everyone has a question
雖然說大家都心中有一問
That is to say, I ate genetically
就是說啊吃了基因的東西
Safety actually went on the market in 1996 until now
安全其實1996年上市到現在
we ate a lot
我們吃了非常多
Because there are very few soybeans grown in Taiwan
因為臺灣種的大豆非常少
More than 90% of the vast majority are imported
絕大部分90%以上都是進口
mostly chicken wings
大部分都是雞翼的
Many bean products on the market are chicken wings
市面上很多的豆類的產品都是雞翼
but we have rules
可是我們有規定
If your protein content reaches 5%
你如果蛋白質含量達到5%
you are going to sign
你就要去標示
so you look carefully
所以你仔細去看
you will see that it is written very small
你就會看到它寫得很小
write about genetic modification
寫說基因改造
Of course there are some Chinese tofu now
當然現在有一些中華豆腐
Printed tofu is non-GMO
印的豆腐它是非基因改造
it writes big
它就寫得很大
Actually there is no need
其實沒有必要
don't worry about that
不用擔心那個
we really eat a lot
我們真的是吃很多
There are many in the world
全球都很多
Human experiments have been done for more than 10 years
人體實驗早就已經做10多年了
no problem
都沒有問題
so don't worry about these things
所以這些東西不用擔心
what are you really worried about
你真的要擔心是什麼
I go to see it every time
我每次都會去看
look at this
看這個啦
What is facial agent
什麼叫臉頭劑
It's just a chemical.
就是售化劑啊
and what preservatives
然後什麼防腐劑啊
biphasic acid
幾二期酸
Then what is the cost of acid and so on
然後什麼本價酸等等
actually a lot
其實非常的多
if you can look carefully
如果你能仔細看
Many foods actually contain these
很多的食物其實裡面都有這些
bring these to the government there are regulations
把這些帶來政府有規定
But is it really at home according to the rules?
可是真的是不是照規定在家
not very clear
也不是很清楚
In fact, often still
其實常常還是會
Occasionally it's on the news
偶爾就是會鬧上新聞
So I will also buy
所以呢我也都會去買
try to buy this
盡量買這個
fog chill preservative stuff
霧寒防腐劑的東西
so this
所以呢這個
this is a worry
這個該擔心的擔心
don't worry about this
不需要擔心的這個
don't need to worry that much
不需要擔心的那麼多
good
好
Then we just mentioned that
那我們剛剛有提到說
the effect on the environment
對環境的影響
This is on the biosafety assessment
這個是在生物安全評估上面
will definitely do
一定會做的
So we already mentioned
所以我們已經提到說
This crop like their insect-resistant
像他們那種抗蟲的這個作物
For this helpful sleepy bug
對於這個有益的困蟲
actually very good
其實是非常好的
so what
所以呢
Definitely do some field biosecurity assessments
一定會做一些田間生物安全評估
For example, will he turn into a weed?
譬如說他會不會變雜草
Possibility of interbreeding with Jinyuan weeds
跟晉元的雜草雜交的可能性
morbid relationship
跟病態的關係
Relationships with other intentional insects, animals, etc.
跟其他有意昆蟲、動物的關係等等
So it's actually under the magnifying glass
所以實際上是在放大鏡底下
View to be able to list
檢視才能夠上市的
Pollen spread is of course possible.
那花粉傳播當然有可能
This is something that many groups keep coming up with.
這個是很多團體是不斷拿出來的
he said you would spread
他說你會傳播
that's actually possible
那實際上是有可能的
But this can be done by a lot of management
可是這個是可以靠很多的管理上面來做
Then we'll review the management later
那我們等一下會再評一下管理
Is this pesticide spraying?
這個是噴農藥會不會
That is to say, those crops that are resistant to insects
就是說那些抗蟲的這些作物
Will it be a problem with intentional insects?
會不會對有意昆蟲有問題
we have just explained
我們剛已經解釋過了
The results done so far show
到現在為止做的結果顯示
there's nothing wrong with it
其實都沒有什麼問題
I'm sorry
那對不起
So this pollen will spread
所以這個花粉會傳播
in what way
可以靠什麼樣的方式
This is an experiment done by Farming
這是農事所做的實驗
you just have to fence it around
你只要四周給它圍離
Or you give it enough isolation space
或是說你給它足夠的隔離的空間
It can separate the pollen
可以把花粉把它隔掉
This is rice research
這個是水稻的研究
You can put genetically modified ones together
你可以一塊放基因轉值的
a piece of non-genetically modified
一塊非基因轉值的
If there is this green mud in the middle, it will be surrounded
中間有這個綠泥就圍起來
Its streaming rate is 0
它的流部率是0
And what about the distance
然後這個距離呢
It's completely 0 at about 40 meters
到差不多40公尺的時候就完全是0
At 35 meters, there will be very little
35公尺的時候還會很少很少
The odds are pretty cool
這個機率就非常冷靜
So in fact the fill-in experiment
所以實際上填兼實驗
You have to do these things to be listed
都要做這些才會上市
So we finally mention that
所以我們最後再提到說
Is genetic food safe?
基因的食品是不是安全呢
Yes
是的
Because they have undergone strict animal safety assessment
因為都經過嚴格的動物安全評估
Then there is one more important thing to say
那還有一個一點很重要說
a lot of this bone
很多的這個骨類
Because insects will eat and have wounds later
因為昆蟲會去吃以後有傷口
then it grows syringa
然後它就會長梅菌
Aflatoxin
梅菌就會產生黃去毒素
This is a very serious factor that can cause cancer
這個是非常嚴重會引致癌症的一個因素
so we sometimes eat this peanut
所以我們有時候在吃這個花生
Especially peanuts imported from Southeast Asia
尤其是東南亞進口的花生
be careful
要很小心
Maybe there are some plums in it
可能裡面就有一些花梅
xanthotoxin
能產生黃去毒素
Then if you eat it, it will cause cancer
然後你吃進去就這個致癌
it's a terrible thing
這是很可怕的事
but they found
可是他們發現
Since these corns with this insect resistance
自從有這種抗蟲的這些玉米之後
The ratio of producing this aflatoxin is greatly reduced
產生這個黃去毒素的這個比例大為降低
So it's not just pesticide reduction
所以不只是農藥減少
It also does not produce aflatoxin
它也不會產生黃去毒素
Nutrients can then be added
然後可以增加營養成分
Then it can correspond to the rapidly increasing population
然後可以對應快速增加的人口
for us in taiwan
對我們台灣來說
This kind of effect can resist insects and diseases
這樣子的能夠抗蟲抗病的作用
is actually very important
其實是非常重要的
Why?
為什麼?
In European and American countries, they are heavily valued
在歐美國家他們大面積重值
He wants something like wet stacking or using pesticides or something
他要嘛像濕疊或是用農藥什麼什麼
It's all done by airplanes
都是飛機在做
Or he has this automatic irrigation system
或是他有這種自動的灌溉系統
But in Southeast Asian countries
可是在東南亞的國家
Much like Taiwan
像台灣很多呢
Many farmers still use their own spray
很多農民還是用自己在噴的
Look, the farmer probably didn't bring anything.
你看這農民大概也沒帶什麼
this security
這個安全防護
This is still very common
這個還是非常普遍
If you really want to play defense
那你真的要玩防護的話
it's ok
也可以啦
But is it possible for farmers to do this?
可是農民可能這樣子去做嗎
All seem to be preventing and treating SARS
全部好像這個在防治SARS的樣子
This is a potato chip from the mainland
這個是大陸的一個馬鈴薯片
them
他們
I don't know how they really defend
我不曉得他們真的是這樣子去防
very strange
很奇怪
OK
OK
anything else
還有呢
Taiwan is actually better now
台灣現在其實好一點
That is to say, there are some rooted systems
就是說有一些帶根制度
there is a special
就是有專門的
Because our villages are aging now
因為我們農村現在都老化嘛
Many farmers are also farming, but they can't move too much.
很多農民也種田也種不太動了
So let others do it
所以都包給人家讓人家去做
Then what
然後呢
In fact, there are some better technical
實際上也有一些比較好技術的
Progressive
比較進步的
It's to use an unmanned aircraft to accompany you.
是用無人飛機去陪伴你偏要
So Taiwan is now also like this
所以台灣現在開始也有這樣子的
but think about it
可是想想
Is it possible that in the future every farmer will be at the edge of the field
有沒有可能將來每個農夫都在田邊
shake the plane there
在那搖空飛機
silly pesticide
傻農藥
I think it would be interesting if there was a day
我想如果能有那一天也能有意思
really passed
真的是非常的經過
But then again
可是這個話說回來
Can we avoid pen and pesticide
可不可以不要 pen and 農藥
Actually it's the most important
其實還是最重要的
Because you need to use pesticides to pen pesticides
因為你 pen 農藥要用農藥
It takes money and energy
又要花錢 又要用能量
then pollute the environment
然後又對環境污染
Then what
然後呢
Mostly farmers
最主要是農民
farmers hurt the most
農民傷害最大
In fact, every year there are farmers
其實每年都有農民
Poisoning yourself from pen pesticides
因為 pen 農藥而自己中毒
so this
所以呢這個
or let the plants themselves
還是讓植物自己本身
resistant to illness
能夠抗病康重
Its benefits are much more
它的好處還是多得多
That plus the amount of pesticides used in Taiwan
那加上台灣的農藥用量
2.5 times the Asian average
亞洲平均的 2.5 倍
5 times that of the US
美國的 5 倍
very scary
很可怕
Because Taiwan is hot and humid
因為台灣高溫多濕
Therefore, those who are particularly prone to long-term weaving are seriously ill
所以特別容易長織的病重康
So I think Taiwan needs to develop
所以我是覺得台灣是特別需要發展
The crop of experience like this
這樣子的經驗的作物
but what about our government
可是我們的政府呢
What about our entire Council of Agriculture?
我們現在整個農委會呢
civil service system
都是公務員體系
they can
他們是可以
This is less wrong
這個少做少錯
this less
這個少
once more is worse than once less
多一次不如少一次
Then it's better not to worry about anything
然後什麼事都最好不要管
So many of our
所以我們的很多的這個
Taiwan's technology is actually very good
台灣的技術其實是很好
we have a lot of good this
我們有很多很好的這個
This product of genetic engineering
基因工程的這個產品
not easy to market
不容易上市
I think our agriculture
我想我們那個農業
National import chemist
國家引進化師
Or agricultural fertility industry plan
或是農業生育產業方案
our people
我們的總處之人
Professor Wu Jinglie is here
吳京烈教授在這邊
he deeply understands
他是深深體會
This one from Taiwan
我們台灣的這個
The potential of our researchers is very good
我們這研究者的潛力是非常好的
We can have many good products
我們可以有很多好的產品
Just told Ang Lee
就跟李安說的
We have a lot of this in Taiwan
我們台灣有很多這個
People who work in the electric business industry
做這個電營產業的人
very talented
非常優秀
But there is no way to play
可是就是沒有辦法發揮
Why
為什麼
think about this
這個要好好的去思考
good
好
So I am very concerned about this issue
所以呢我很關心這個問題
So I often write articles
所以我常常就會寫文章
Then what
然後呢
strangeness
奇怪
His computer will run by itself today
他這個電腦今天會自己跑
Eh
欸
Oops
糟糕
OK
OK
i will write
我就會寫說
GM crops
基改作物
this is me
這個是我在
This was about two years ago
這個大概是兩年前
then in china
然後在中國
I just published
我就發表了
I said whether machine-modified crops are the hope of Taiwan's agriculture
我說機改作物是不是台灣農業的希望
But it must be expected
可是一定可以預期的
There must be an objection soon
馬上一定就有人來反對
Machine-modified crops still come and should be dealt with
機改作物仍然來應該省勝應對
So the professor at National Taiwan University
所以台大的教授
Academician He Danghua
這個賀當華院士
He also wrote an article
他就也寫了一篇文章
He said that this machine-modified crop is due to rational discussion
他說這個機改作物因理性討論
what is the most important
最主要是什麼
Because we really haven't had a rational discussion
因為我們真的一直沒有理性討論
Everyone is open and transparent
大家公開透明
The pros and cons
這個好處壞處
discuss it
大家討論出來
let everyone know
讓大家了解
Then we choose
然後我們來選擇
should we do this
我們要不要這樣子做
You let me choose experience not to spray pesticides
你讓我選擇經驗不噴農藥
It's still a non-experienced person who doesn't spray pesticides
還是一個非經驗不噴農藥
I think I have to choose experience instead of spraying pesticides
我覺得我要選擇經驗不噴農藥
real
真的
After we understand his nature
在我們了解他的本質之後
I also recently wrote an article
我最近也寫了一篇文章
That is to say, machine-modified crops are actually a political issue.
就是說機改作物其實是政治問題
real
真的
We just talked about a lot of issues
我們剛剛講了很多的問題
if you scientifically
如果你科學角度來說
he's not a problem
他都不是問題
But this government
可是這個政府
Between countries is often because of political factors
國與國之間常常就是因為政治因素
So he will block his development
所以他就會去阻擋他的發展
very pity
非常的可惜
what are the consequences of this
這造成什麼樣的後果
you won't let me
你這個不讓
look first
先看
Look at this anti-pest and disease-resistant words
看這個抗蟲抗病的話
You have a lot of pesticides
你農藥就有很多嘛
who makes money
那誰賺錢
Pesticide companies make money
農藥公司賺錢
so what
所以呢
You crop that prevents us from developing these experiences
你這個阻止我們發展這些經驗的作物
You are helping the pesticide company
你就是在幫助農藥公司
anything else
還有呢
Gold just now and you too
剛剛黃金你也是一樣
2 million for experiment
兩百萬來做實驗
20 million for biosafety assessment
兩千萬來做生物安全評估
I have been doing it for ten years and finally found that there is no problem at all.
做了十年到最後發現一點問題都沒有
really no problem at all
真的一點都問題都沒有
but who did you help
可是你幫了誰
You helped those agbiotech companies
你幫了那些農業生技公司
The world's largest agricultural biotechnology companies
全球那些大的農業生技公司
Because only he can afford 20 million to do it
因為只有他富得起兩千萬來做
biosafety assessment
這樣子生物安全評估
Many of our small laboratories
我們很多的小的研究室
small company
小的公司
spend so much money to do this
花那麼多錢去做這件事情
so who did you help
所以你幫了誰
You just helped the big companies
你就是幫了那些大公司
Only he has money to do things
只有他有錢可以做事
so why now
所以為什麼現在
Make money by experience crops
靠經驗作物在賺錢的
those big companies
就是那些大公司
So this has a lot to think about
所以這個有很多要思考的地方
then i have been
那我是一直
In addition, it has been emphasized that
另外也一直在強調說
why should we hurry
為什麼我們要趕快
Actively do research
積極做研究
Although our government does not promote
雖然我們的政府不推廣
but he
可是他
He can still let us do research
他還是可以讓我們做研究
Guo Kewei
尤其是國柯衛
he is really nice
他是真的是很好
That is to say, there is still a lot of money
就是說還是很多的經費
let's do research
讓我們做研究
because we really want to master
因為我們真的要掌握
Hold this upstream patent
掌握這個上游的專利
upgrade
升級
Our IT industry is already suffering
我們的IT產業已經是深受其苦
There are many upstream patents that cannot be grasped
有很多的上游專利掌握不到
so what
所以呢
Every hundred dollars you sell
你每賣出一百塊錢的
mobile phone is likely these
手機很可能這些
like iphone
像iPhone
This Apple makes fifty bucks
這個Apple賺五十塊錢
Taiwan probably only earns one or two dollars
台灣大概只能賺一塊兩塊
Patents are in the hands of others
專利都在人家的手中
So biotechnology is the same
所以生技也是一樣
Especially the good genes of this crop now
尤其是現在這個作物的好的基因
if you look online
你如果上網去看
A lot of genes every day
每天都很多的基因
Patented by these biotech companies
都被這些生技公司專利掉了
If we don't speed up our research
我們如果不加速研究的話
In the future, we will use it ourselves in Taiwan
將來我們臺灣自己要用
You have to pay other people's money
你還要去付人家的錢
So this is a pretty stressful thing
所以這個是蠻令人緊張的一件事情
so why we've been active
所以為什麼我們一直很積極
doing these research and development
在做這些研發
In fact, many scientists around the world
其實全球很多的科學家
Both support this genetically modified crop
都支持這個基因改良的作物
this is just an example
這個只是例子
American Institute for Employment
譬如說美國職務學會
Royal Society
英國皇家學會
In fact, if you look online
事實上你如果上網去看
There are many, many groups like this that are very supportive
有非常非常多這樣子的團體都很支持
Finally I want to tell this story
最後我要講這個故事
This is January 5 this year
這個是今年1月5號
Newsweek posted a message
Newsweek登出來一個消息
many people don't notice
很多人沒有注意到
He posted such a photo
他登出來這樣一個照片
Metro in Paris, France on February 15, 2011
在11年2月15號在法國巴黎的地鐵
Photo taken at the subway station
地鐵站照到
You see he uses this corn as a gun
你看他把這個玉米當作一個槍
to hit someone on the head
要打一個人的頭
So I think what he means is probably
所以我想他的意思大概
I don't understand this French
這法文我看不懂
I think some students are from France
我好像有學生是法國來的
He might understand this
他說不定這個看得懂
I mean genetically modified stuff
意思是說基因改造的東西
It seems that if you eat people, what will happen?
好像會把人吃了就會怎麼樣
what will happen if you die
會死會怎麼樣子
So he put a picture like this
所以他放這樣子的照片
But his article
可是他那一篇文章
What is New Swick really going to talk about
New Swick真的要講的事情是什麼
He wants to talk about this gentleman
他要講這位先生
Called Mark Nymus
叫做Mark Nymus
this mr.
這個先生
this gentleman said
這個先生他說
he was surprised
他很意外
Mr. He apologized
這個先生他道歉
sorry for what
道歉什麼事情呢
for him for many years
為他過去很多年來
Probably more than twenty years
大概是二十多年吧
Anti-gene behavior like this
反基因的這樣子的行為
Everyone is surprised why
大家很意外 為什麼
Because he is a very famous environmentalist
因為他是一個非常有名的環境保護學家
I have been anti-experience, I have been advocating
一直在反經驗 一直在鼓吹
Can't eat this experience
不能吃這個經驗的東西
then he apologized
然後他就道歉
Then this article in this Newsweek
然後這個Newsweek裡面講的這個文章
He's saying experience won't be a problem for us
他是說經驗對我們不會有什麼問題
your real problem now
你現在真正的問題
where is the real crisis
真正的危機是在哪裡
but the minority in rich countries
而是那些有錢的國家的少數的人
He insisted on eating very natural food
他堅持要吃很天然的食物
But in the future, they will fight back because of their behavior
可是將來因為他們這樣子反擊眼
You will starve many, many people around the world
你會讓全球很多很多人都餓死
So in his article
所以他的這個文章裡面
This has this website here
這個有這個網站在這邊
So the main question is to go back to what I just said
所以最主要的問題就是回到我剛剛講的說
Now the global food article is getting bigger
現在全球糧食的文章是越來越大
And this Mark Niners
那這位的Mark Niners
He's a real environmentalist
他是一個真正的環境保護學家
He was born in Oxford, England, quite young
他是出生於英國牛津 還滿年輕的
he is a famous writer
那他是一個很有名的作家
journalists and environmentalists
記者跟環境保護者
I've also written many books and made movies.
也寫過很多書 也拍過電影
mostly related to issues of environmental change
主要都跟環境變遷的議題有關
In a recent public lecture in Oxford, England, he
他最近在英國牛津的一場公開演講中
Publicly apologized for his anti-GN actions since the 1990s
為他自1990年代開始反GN的行動公開道歉
Because he thinks that as an environmentalist
因為他認為身為一個環境保護者
This new technology will be mindful of the global environment
這個新科技將對全球的環境有注意
When he first heard about Mansanto's GN soybeans
他第一次聽到曼山都的GN大豆的時候
He thinks this product will pollute food and our environment
他認為這個產品會污染食物跟我們的環境
It is something that cannot be done with high technology
是利用高科技做不到的事情
what a nightmare
簡直是惡夢一場
So they started spreading the fear
所以他們就開始把這種恐懼就開始擴散
like wildfire
如野火遼原般
Made GN Friday almost banned in Europe within a few years
使得GN周五在幾年之內在歐洲幾乎被禁止
This fear is also exported by the Calendar Peace Organization and Friends of the Earth
這種恐懼也被歷社和平組織跟地球之友外銷
to Africa, India, Asia
到非洲、印度、亞洲
The development of genetic organization is affected
使得基因組織的發展受到影響
This Mark thinks his activity
這個Mark他認為他這個活動
It's the most successful event he's ever been involved in
是他所參與過最成功的活動
most successful sport
最成功的運動
What about after 2008?
那在2008年之後呢
someone asked him
就有人問他了
He says you're against agribiotech
他說你反對農業生技公司的
because of opposition to agribiotech companies
因為反對農業生技公司
you against genes
你而反對基因
So will you also be against big car companies?
那你會不會也因為反對汽車大公司
And against the car?
而反對汽車呢
So this time he started
所以這時候他就開始
learn from science
根據科學來瞭解
Causes of Environmental Change
環境變遷的原因
Meaning with experience crops
跟經驗作物的意義
Then his warship found
那他軍艦發現說
Empirical technology can indeed solve
經驗技術的確是可以解決
Rapidly deteriorating environmental change and population issues
極速極速惡化的環境變遷跟人口問題
Just like the issues I mentioned earlier in my speech today
就如同我今天演講前面所講的那些問題
in his article
在他的文章裡面
All written into a very long article
全部都寫出來一篇非常長的文章
So we scientifically
所以我們從科學的角度上
look at this question
來看這個問題
Experience definitely pays off
經驗絕對是對人有利的
that to our future world
那對我們未來的世界
it is needed
它是需要
it may not solve all problems
它不一定能解決所有的問題
But we don't have much choice now
可是我們現在沒有太多的選擇
We still have to hurry up and develop this technology
我們還是必須要趕快來研發這個技術
let it provide us with safety
讓它可以提供我們安全
Then this can protect the environment
然後這個對環境又可以保護
Then it can cope with the future population
然後又可以應付未來人口的
a very important strategy
一個很重要的一個策略
ok then i'll end up here
好 那我就最後在這邊結束
I believe us scientists
我相信我們這些科學家
No one wants to hurt anyone
沒有一個是想要害人的
We all want to say that based on good science
我們都希望說以良好科學為基礎
to make the greatest contribution to mankind
來為人類做出最大的貢獻
so thank you guys
所以謝謝各位
Thanks
謝謝
The first time I came to the professor to check the examination
我第一次來教授檢查的檢查
He's dreamed about the time
他已經夢幻說了時間了
Usually I just move on as soon as it's out
通常我是一過時就要繼續
I am doing textbooks today
我今天因為進行科書
our ten minute chance
我們十分鐘的機會
or the end of the ninety-sixty minutes
或者九六十分鐘的結束的話
so we ask
所以我們就請教
I'm sorry to ask Professor Yu
請教於教授不好意思
i ask simple questions
我問簡單的問題
that means we buy food
就是說我們買食物
When buying fruits and vegetables, do you buy the ones you have never eaten?
買蔬果是不是買那個從吃過的
It will be safer to eat like this
這樣吃會比較安全
Thanks
謝謝
Yes, many people will ask this question
對啊 很多人會問這個問題
Of course that shows
當然那個顯示出
it is possible to show that
有可能顯示出說
Pesticides may be used less
農藥可能是少用一點
but how much is it really used
可是是真的用多少
I think it's still hard to say
我覺得這個還是很難講
and then the other one is
然後另外一個是
We have a lot of bugs now
我們現在很多蟲很厲害
already resistant
已經有抗藥性
So you can't kill him with spray
所以你噴藥也殺不死
so it will die
所以它照樣會死
So it's really the best
所以呢真的是最好啦
better i think
最好我是覺得
Plants themselves are resistant to insects and pesticides
植物自己本身能夠抗蟲抗藥
still more important
還是比較重要
But someone still has a potential problem
可是有人還是有一個潛在的問題
That is to say, sometimes these bugs
就是說有時候這些蟲
germs it hardens
病炎菌它會變硬
So it is not easy for you to come across a good breed
所以呢你毫不容易遇出來一個好的品種
Not long after, the ingredient disease came again
沒隔多久這個成分病又來了
But the traditional breed is worse
可是傳統品種更糟糕
Sometimes it takes you 10 years
有時候你毫不容易花了10年
meet a species
遇出來一個品種
two or three years to come
兩三年就到了
Came because of serious illness
因為病重害就來了
But at least we now have genetic engineering to compete with it
可是至少我們現在基因工程可以跟它比賽
race it
跟它賽跑
see who is faster
看誰快
you get very sick and get sick fast
你病重炎變得快
I am also very fast with my genetic modification technology
我的基因轉值技術我也很快
So at least we still have some strategy to follow it
所以至少我們還有一些策略可以跟它
deal with it like this
對付它這樣子
please tell me
這請教一下
When I buy soybeans, I always buy the one with the fat gene.
我買黃豆都一定買那個肥基因的
Is there no need to do this anymore?
那此後是不是不需要再這樣
I think there should be no need to worry about that
我想應該是不需要有那樣子的顧慮
because we eat a lot
因為我們吃很多
you are at home of course you can do this
你在家裡當然你可以這樣做
But we know that there are really many people who eat out
可是我們知道外食的人真的很多
What do we people who eat out eat out every day?
我們外食的人到底每天在外面吃什麼東西
really don't know
真的也不清楚
Genetic soybeans are still cheaper
因為基因的大豆還是比較便宜
So I believe that many business people will still buy that kind of
所以我相信很多做生意人還是會買那一種的
right
對
The most important thing is that he has been from 1996 to now
最主要是他已經1996年到現在
It's been 16 years
已經16年了
16 years have passed
16年的時間已經經過
I believe we have many things on the market
我相信我們市面上有很多東西
including a lot of medical stuff
包括很多醫學的東西
No one can guarantee 100% that there will be no problems.
都沒有人可以保證百分之百不會有問題
But in fact, the genetic thing is up to now
可是實際上基因的東西到現在
really didn't happen a problem
真的沒有發生一個問題
right
對
grateful
感謝
OK
OK
teacher please
老師請問一下
How can we prevent certain
要怎麼樣讓我們能夠阻止某一些
Similar to Monsanto
類似像孟山圖公司
Because they're pretty notorious.
因為他們的確是蠻惡名昭彰的
That is, he has a lot of varieties
就是他有很多的一些品種
He is the one who protected himself
就是他自己保護住了
If so
那這樣子的話
Countries should develop biotechnology
各國要發展生物科技
also a big problem
也是一個很大的問題
In fact, there are many genes
其實基因還有很多
there are many more available
還有很多可以用
It's not that only the genes he used can be used
不是說只有他用的基因可以用
So why should we all step up our research
所以為什麼我們大家要加強研究的原因
that's it
就是這樣子
But what?
可是呢
Too bad only these big companies have money
糟糕的是只有這些大公司有錢
Can be pushed from R&D to product
可以從研發推到商品
he can
他可以
Get through every level and every level like this
每一關每一關這樣子打通
but what about us
可是我們呢這些
Compared with these small companies with no money
比較沒有錢的這些小公司啊
small research institute
小的研究機構啊
you have to start from scratch
你要從頭做大尾
It's really tough
真的很難
So the government is in terms of policy
所以呢政府啊在政策上面
on the counseling
在輔導上面
still have to play an important role
還是要扮演很重要的角色
Now the most important thing is to say
那現在最主要就是說
If you know the nature of this gene
你若認識這個基因的本質
If you don't use such strict standards
如果你不要用這麼嚴格的標準
Taiwanese
臺灣的
genetic criteria
基因的標準
I think it is almost the strictest in the world now
我覺得現在幾乎是全世界上最嚴的
real
真的
Now
現在
In fact, everything in Taiwan depends on Japan
臺灣其實什麼東西都看日本
why did we go
為什麼我們過去
It seems that everyone has an excuse
好像啊大家都有藉口
Talk about our rice in Taiwan or something
說我們臺灣的米啊什麼的
Can't have genes
不能有基因的
Because we sell it to Japan
因為我們銷到日本去啊
Japan will not buy it or something
日本就就會不買啊什麼的
you in that papaya
你在那個木瓜
Prof. Yi Xidong from Taiwan's famous Sino-British University
台灣很有名的中英大學易錫東教授
antiviral papaya
抗病毒的木瓜
After he developed more than ten years ago
他在十多年前發展出來以後
At that time, papayas in Taiwan were almost extinct.
那一陣子台灣的木瓜幾乎快要絕種
only later to the east
只有後來到東部去
Because of the barrier of important mountains
因為重要山脈阻隔
can also hit a little bit
還可以中到一點
but later
可是後來
Teacher Ye's Hard Papaya
葉老師的基硬的木瓜
Field experiment conducted by Zhongzai Agriculture
中在農事所做田間試驗
The farmer saw that his papaya was growing well
農民看到居然他的木瓜長得好好的
All other papayas are dead, only he is good
別的木瓜都死光了只有他好的
stole the seeds
偷了種子
then go back to plant
然後就回去種
So a few years ago Zhao Yongqing legislator
所以幾年前趙詠卿立委
I still remember to ask
我還記得就去質問
He said why Taiwan now heard that the test
他說為什麼台灣現在聽說試驗上
One-third to one-quarter of papayas are
有三分之一到四分之一的木瓜是
GM's might be even higher
GM的說不定還更高
because almost for a while
因為幾乎是有一陣子都沒有
Now we have papaya because
現在我們有吃到木瓜是因為
Article scraping relationship
刮文章的關係
So his GM papaya farmer went planting
所以他那個GM的木瓜農民去種
Then, don’t many of our farmers go to the mainland to grow agricultural products?
然後呢 我們不是很多農民都到大陸去種農產品嗎
So he brought his chicken papaya to the mainland to plant
所以把他的這個雞肉木瓜又拿到大陸去種
Then Mr. Ye went to Hainan Island
然後葉老師他就到那個海南島啊
He went to the supermarket to buy a papaya
超市他就去買了一棵木瓜
dig out the seeds
把種子挖出來
Go to a supermarket in Beijing for a meeting
到北京的超市去開會
He bought another papaya and dug up that seed
他又買了一棵木瓜把那個種子挖出來
When he came back to Taiwan and checked, it was his papaya
他回台灣來一檢查就是他的木瓜
Hehehe
呵呵呵
So the mainland is already eating everywhere
所以大陸已經到處都在吃了
Then Hawaii developed at about the same time as him
然後夏威夷跟他差不多同時發展出來的
Genetically engineered papayas are also virus-resistant
基因轉職的木瓜也是抗病毒的
It has been commercialized for ten years
已經商業化十年了
As for Taiwan, he is constantly being suppressed and blocked.
台灣這邊呢 他就是不斷的被壓下來 被阻擋
Then our chairman of the Agricultural Committee said
然後呢 我們的農委會主委就說
look at this
你看啊 這個
This is because Japanese papayas are all from Hawaii
這個因為日本的木瓜都是從夏威夷
for export
外銷的嘛
He said you see Japanese people don't even eat Hawaiian papayas
他說你看日本人都不吃夏威夷的木瓜
So how about this, we cannot develop in Taiwan
所以這個怎麼樣我們台灣不能發展
so really for a while
所以真的是有一陣子
Hawaii had to be special for Japan
夏威夷只好為了日本特別
Because he has many islands
因為他有很多島嘛
So on the island he has, he specially planted this
所以他有的島他就特別種這個
Airplane colorful papaya
飛機艷的木瓜
Export to Japan, right?
外銷日本對不對
But the September of the previous year
可是前年的9月
Japan has passed the import
日本已經通過可以進口
Hawaii's genetically modified papaya
夏威夷的基因轉職的木瓜了
Our papaya is still pressed there
我們的木瓜還在壓在那裡
Biotechnology is actually progressing very fast
生技的東西其實進步速度非常快
everyone is competing
大家都都在競爭
We are often treated like this by the government
我們常常被政府這樣子
After pressing down
壓下來以後
Our competitiveness is lost
我們的競爭力都喪失掉了
So this genetic thing
所以這個基因的東西
This big company has his deep pockets
這個大公司是有他財力雄厚
But also because of the help of environmental groups
可是也因為環保團體的幫忙
So it is still only the big companies that can
所以變成還是只有大公司能夠
able to dominate the market
能夠主導這個市場
Thanks
謝謝
During GM, we should talk about native species of biodiversity
GM的時候跟生物多樣性的原生種這方面
How can we find this balance
怎麼能夠尋求這個平衡
i want biodiverse people
我想生物多樣性的人
Of course, I hope to be able to find things in nature
當然很希望能夠自然界中的東西
don't change too much
不要太多改變
But I just mentioned that many
可是我剛剛也提到其實很多
In fact, it keeps changing
其實一直就不斷的在改變
We humans add some genes to this crop
我們人類把這個作物加上一些基因
Then we're between different balances
然後我們在不同的平衡之間
exchange it
給它交換
In fact, we are promoting diversity
其實我們是在促進多樣性
So it's not reducing diversity
所以並不是在減少多樣性
Instead, it promotes diversity
反而是促進多樣性
This human looks like this
這個人類這樣子
This creature has evolved over the years
這個生物演化這麼多年來
In fact, many processes
其實很多的過程
Of course not anytime soon
當然不是很快就發生了
it's been a long time
它是經過長久的時間
Our humans are just speeding it up now
我們的人類現在只是加快它的速度而已
In fact, there are many things in nature
其實裡面很多的事情自然界中
it's been happening
本來就一直在發生了
Then I think if the population is not increasing so fast
那我覺得如果人口不是增加速度那麼快
If it weren't for the fact that our environment has been deteriorating
如果不是因為我們的環境一直在惡化當中
We don't necessarily have to develop experiential stuff either.
我們也不一定要發展經驗的東西
But now I think the most important thing is that the population growth rate is too fast
可是現在我想最主要是人口增加速度太快了
Then pesticide use has a lot
然後農藥使用有很多
The cost for farmers to follow the crowd has been rising
農民跟眾的成本又一直在上升
So there are many kinds of problems
所以有很多種種的問題
Let's not face problems like this
讓我們不得來面對這樣子的問題
I think if you can not
我想如果可以不要的話
we better not do
我們也最好不要做
yes
是
well the time has come
好 時間已經到了
we thank the hospital today
我們今天謝謝醫院
thank you
謝謝各位
Thanks
謝謝